<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three sermons preached by VVilliam Sclater Doctor of Diuinity, and minister of the word of God at Pitmister in Sommersetshire. Now published by his sonne of Kings Colledge in Cambridge</title>
            <author>Sclater, William, 1575-1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1629</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11605</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21846</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102973</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838732</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838732</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3120</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11605)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3120)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1155:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three sermons preached by VVilliam Sclater Doctor of Diuinity, and minister of the word of God at Pitmister in Sommersetshire. Now published by his sonne of Kings Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                  <author>Sclater, William, 1575-1626.</author>
                  <author>Sclater, William, 1609-1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 16, [8], 17-39, [11], 19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Harper for Robert Allot, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church yard at the signe of the blacke Beare,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1629.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Edited by William Sclater the younger.</note>
                  <note>"A sermon preached at St. Maries in the Vniversity of Cambridge", "A sermon preached at Tanton in Sommerset", and "A funerall sermon preached at the buriall of the Right Worshipfull Mr. Iohn Colles Esquier" have separate title pages; register is continuous; "A funerall sermon" has separate pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3120:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3120:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THREE SERMONS Preached by WILLIAM SCLA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER Doctor of Diuinity, and Miniſter of the word of God at <hi>Pitmiſter</hi> in <hi>Sommerſetſhire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now publiſhed by his Sonne of Kings</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device of Thomas Harper</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by THOMAS HARPER for <hi>Robert Allot,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church yard at the ſigne of the blacke Beare. 1629.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3120:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3120:2"/>
                  <p>SERMON Preached at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Maries</hi> in the Vniuerſity of <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By WILLIAM SCLATER Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of Diuinity, ſometimes Fellow of <hi>Kings Colledge, and Miniſter of the word of God at</hi> Pitmiſter <hi>in Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſetſhire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now publiſhed by his Sonne of the ſame Kings Colledge in</hi> Cambridge.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by THOMAS HARPER for <hi>Robert Allot,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church yard at the ſigne of the blacke Beare. 1629.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3120:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3120:3"/>
                  <head>To that pious root of Religion and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, <hi>the worſhipfull and deuout gentlewoman, Miſtriſſe IANE STILL,</hi> Together with her tender branches at <hi>Hutton</hi> in Sommerſet, <hi>William Sclater</hi> wiſheth all happineſſe and proſperity in this life, and that which is to come.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Moſt worthy Matron:</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O auoyd the imputation of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude this ſlender Epiſtle of mine proſtrates it ſelfe to your fauourable acceptation, deſiring (though meanely) to expreſſe its Authours ſeruice, and (that indubitate office &amp; act of loue) his thankfulneſſe for that abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of kindneſſe, couetesy and well-willing, which from the infancy of your acquaintance with our deare Father, has beene from you propagated to vs branches of that root. Were it not, that I ſhould be fouly iniurious to a Saint in Heauen (the memory of whom, as of a iuſt man is for euer bleſſed) I could
<pb facs="tcp:3120:4"/> willingly deſire the accompliſhment of that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> which once ſome, (though in another caſe) ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing vnder the Statue of <hi>Brutus,</hi> made, <hi>would G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> thou wert aliue Brutus!</hi> ſo I, would heauen would reſtore him, whoſe image externally I beare, &amp; hope to be made heire of thoſe vertues (the beſt inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance) reſplendent in him, that hee might himſelfe haue preſented you with this badge of his thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the contrary whereof was euer odious to him, and abhorrent from his nature; but ſince I cannot craue the fruition of his preſence without bereauing him of felicity, let this gratefull office tendred by his Sonne haue acceſſe at the barre of your courteous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation, and if it (weighed in the ballance of your rich fauours) come ſhort of equall counterpoizing them, you may in part aſcribe it to the tenuity of the enditers immature iudgement, and want of rhetoricke to ſet it downe, but chiefly to the greatneſſe of your kindneſſe, which tranſcends the capacity of ſo illite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate a pen-man; but what you finde defectiue on my part, ſuppoſe (if there be any ſence of ſuch things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Saints in Heauen) to be ſupplyed by the approbation of him, whoſe ſonne I was. The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent here offered vnto you is a Sermon preached by the Authour, my deceaſed Father, at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Maries</hi> in the Vniuerſity of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> when he commenced Doctor of Diuinity, which through the importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſome my worthy friends, and men of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who wiſh well to the Common-wealth of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, I haue put to the preſſe, hoping, that when it's brought forth, and expoſed to the open world, it may finde ſafe ſhelter, and protection vnder the wings of
<pb facs="tcp:3120:4"/> your patronage. In it it you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y furtherance of your faith, I dare promiſe for the Author, that he hath his deſire; as for my ſelfe, be pleaſed thus to thinke, I had rather be accounted any thing, then vnthankfull. Now, the God of all grace, that hath called you to his eternall glory by Chriſt Ieſus, make you perfect, confirme, ſtrengthen and ſtabliſh you in the true faith of his ſonne, deliuer you from euery e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill worke, and preſerue you to his heauenly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours deuoted in all thankfull obſeruance <hi>WILLIAM SCLATER.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From my Chamber in Kings Colledge in Cambridge.</hi>
                        <date>Nou. 18. 1628.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3120:5"/>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, be pleaſed co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly to embrace what not mine owne, but the maturity of others iudgements haue thought worthy the Preſſe. The Authours whole purpoſe euer was to heale, if poſsible, the breaches of Gods people, and further the fayth of his Church. Where he is faulty, ſmite him friendly, it ſhall be balme to the heades of his poſterity, and perhaps a meanes, that the remnant of his labours re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound heereafter to the Churches good. Now the Lord ſole giuer of increaſe to the painefull inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors of his Miniſters, make this part of his works fruitfull, to the comfort of thy conſcience, and eſtabliſhment of thy fayth. Amen.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Thine in Chriſt</hi> W. S.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3120:5"/>
                  <head>THE SPIRITVALL <hi>War-fare.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1. PETER. 2.11.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>Dearely beloued, I beſeech you as ſtrangers and pilgrimes, abſtaine from fleſhly luſts which war againſt the Soule.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Text is amongſt thoſe, that <hi>antiquo vocabulo,</hi> but <hi>nouo erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re</hi> yee call precedents: let that be no preiudice to the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of it.</p>
                  <p>The reſolution is plainly this: We haue firſt a Preface inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue; wherein firſt a louing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a meeke obteſtation, <hi>I beſeech you.</hi> Secondly, an exhortation; wherein, 1. the Act, <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine,</hi> ſecondly the obiect <hi>fleſhly luſts,</hi> thirdly Reaſons
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3120:6"/> preſſing the exhortation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> firſt from our ſtate; <hi>We are ſtranger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> and pilgrimes;</hi> ſecondly, from their d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ect; <hi>They warre againſt the Soule:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> It is no title of complement, but a true Character of Paſtorall affection. And howſoeuer proteſtations of this nature be not alwaies neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; yet the thing is that muſt ſeaſon all miniſteriall performances. Whether he exhort, or inſtruct, or reproue, or correct, here muſt that haue place in a Miniſter that S. <hi>Paul</hi> preſcribes to the people:<note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 16 14.</note> 
                     <hi>That all our things be done in loue.</hi> The high Prieſt in the old Law, when he goes to Miniſter before the Lord in behalfe of the people, muſt haue in his<note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 28. &amp; 39.</note> Breaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate ingrauen the names of the Tribes of Iſrael; on his breaſt the ſeale of loue; to ſignifie with what entire affection, a Paſtour of the Church ſhould be deuoted to the good of his people. There is indeed a kind of loue, the bane of all Paſtorall perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, in effect hatred rather then loue. Let me therefore remember vnto you that ancient pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of <hi>Hierome</hi> to husbands in reſpect of their wiues: A wiſe man muſt loue his wife, <hi>indici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> non affectu;</hi> Iudiciouſly, rather then affectionately<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo muſt a Paſtors loue be guided by iudgeme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not by affection. <hi>Grecians</hi> haue well d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed them by their names<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the one they call <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the other <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> blind affection, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and doting loue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t drawes with it, firſt a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placentiam, a kind of pleaſance, and contentment in very deformities and greateſt blemiſhes. <hi>Balbinum delectat polypus Agnae.</hi> And the lukewarme, worſt temper of the Soule in deuotion, begins amongſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3120:6"/> Paſtors to be their peoples commendation. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> A <hi>nimium</hi> of couniuence at the groſſeſt ſinnes till cuſtome haue brought vpon them the dy of the Blackemore, and their ſpots become as thoſe of the<note n="c" place="margin">Ier. 13.23.</note> 
                     <hi>Leopard,</hi> neuer (except by miracle) to be remoued. Thirdly, Indulgence and flattery: Goe vp and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ſay <hi>Achabs</hi> Chaplaines: there are minims of duties: the Prodigall, ſuch call liberall; the Couetous, good husbands; tatling, in the ſtile of flatterys is affability; pertinacie, fortitude; very ſloath; ſtaied<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and maturity of iudgement; enormities are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities; neuer ſo little morality, purity no leſſe then Angelicall. <hi>Its magna ira dej,</hi> ſayth S. <hi>Auſtin, vt defit correctio, &amp; adfit adulatio.</hi> The complaint of <hi>Hierome</hi> befits theſe times; <hi>In multis iſto ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xime tempore regnat hoc vitium; quodque eſt grauiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimum, humilitatis ac beneuolentiae loco ducitur: eò fit vt qui adularj neſcit aut inuidus aut Superbus</hi>
                     <note n="1" place="margin">Hieron ad Caelantium.</note> 
                     <hi>putetur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The other kind of loue onely Commendable in a Miniſter is, diſcreet Chriſtian Charitie; ordinate loue, not inordinate affection. It drawes with it compaſſion of miſery, ſupply of wants, ſeaſonable<note n="a" place="margin">Leuit. 19.17.</note> 
                     <hi>reproofe</hi> and <hi>correction,</hi> when the ſtate of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple requires it. <hi>Shall I</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.21.</note> 
                     <hi>come with the rod, or in loue, and in the ſpirit of meekeneſſe?</hi>
                     <note n="2" place="margin">Aug. contra. epiſt. Parmen. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Nunquid tamen &amp; virga ſine Charit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eſt? &amp; virga charitatem habet. Sed aliud eſt cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>tas feuerti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>is, aliud chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> dinit: vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> quidem charitas eſt, ſed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſa in diuerſis operatur</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Sometimes yee may obſerue Gods ſeruants more peremptory: S. <hi>Paul</hi> not onely<note n="c" place="margin">2. Tim. 2.14 &amp; 4.1.</note> 
                     <hi>chargeth,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Timothy,</hi> to do the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3120:7"/> office of an Euangeliſt, preſcribes him to charge the rich in this world to be rich in faith. And <hi>Titus</hi> to<note n="d" place="margin">Tit. 2.</note> ſpeake, <hi>exhort, rebuke;</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> with all peremptorineſſe of commanding. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſaith S. <hi>Paul:</hi> the Lord hath giuen vs power to vſe<note n="e" place="margin">2 Cor. 13.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> ſharpeneſſe, as well as commanded meekeneſſe, where it tends to edification, not to deſtruction. Its ſaid indeed; the Lord was<note n="f" place="margin">1 Reg. 19.11.</note> 
                     <hi>not in the wind, nor in the earth-quake, nor in the fire, but in the ſtill voice;</hi> Yet its true, Gods voyce is as well in the terrible <hi>thunder</hi> of threates, as in the meeke allurements by promiſes and ſoft ſpeeches, except perhaps we may ſay, he ſpake onely by <hi>Barnabas,</hi> the ſonne of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation; and not alſo by thoſe <hi>Boanerges,</hi> the ſons of thunder.</p>
                  <p>What may be our direction in prudence? Firſt the rule is ancient: <hi>Suum quemque decet.</hi> The Maieſtie, and peremptory ſpirit of <hi>Elias</hi> reſts not on all the ſonnes of the Prophets; as on <hi>Eliza<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> Some are rather of <hi>Moſes</hi> his temper, meeke euer to admiration. The Lord of all gifts diſtributes<note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 12.</note> ſeuerally: and here it hath place of the Apoſtle; Euery man hath his<note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 7.7.</note> proper gift, one after this manner, another after that. Its not ſafe ſtrayning againſt our peculiar inclinations. Secondly, Beſides we muſt learne to diſtinguiſh, firſt perſons, ſecondly States of perſons, thirdly, parts of miniſtery.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> There are ſome of a brazen forhead, and yron ſinew; with ſuch to deale mildly were to beate the ayre: with theſe it muſt haue place that <hi>Ieremy</hi> hath; Gods word muſt be as<note n="c" place="margin">Ierem. 23.29.</note> fire, and as the hammer to breake the ſtone. There are others of <hi>Ioſias</hi> temper,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3120:7"/> the noyſe of any thing fearefull reſolues, and makes euen to melt: theſe if we meekely perſwade, and allure, as<note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>Noah</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>Iapheth</hi> we ſhall ſooner bring them into the tents of <hi>Shem.</hi> This is Saint <hi>Iudes</hi> rule; haue<note n="e" place="margin">Iud. ver 22.23.</note> compaſſion on ſome in putting difference; others ſaue with feare pulling them out of fire. S. <hi>Bernard</hi> alluding to that in the <hi>Pſalme:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>1.</hi> Bernard. Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent cap. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> there is <hi>virga</hi> and <hi>Baculus:</hi> his rule is this: <hi>virgâ ouem, baculo lupum i.e. mites &amp; obedientes,</hi> we muſt <hi>leuius corripere; duros verò corde, &amp; improbos, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criùs arguere, cum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> neceſſe fuit, Anathematis ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiâ ferire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Euen Gods children, and people muſt be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> in a double ſtate. Euen<note n="f" place="margin">2. Theſ. 3.6.</note> brethren ſometimes walke inordinately. In this caſe the Lord himſelfe writes bitter things againſt them, hee is very<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 89.</note> terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the aſſembly of the Saints: in ſuch caſe <hi>Moſes</hi> the mirror of meekeneſſe bids Leuites gird with the<note n="h" place="margin">Exod. 32.</note> ſword. And<note n="i" place="margin">1 Cor. 5.5.</note> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> deliuers to Satan, that the fleſh may be deſtroyed. Thirdly, there are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall parts, and workes of our Miniſtery; wherin <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ſeuerall graces muſt be exerciſed: prudence and loue muſt direct all: but mildneſſe or auſterity appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated to particulars. Firſt inſtruct with meekeneſſe; too much heate in inſtruction addes little grace to the teacher or hearer. That <hi>Grande dicendi genus</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> likes not, in deliuering doctrines for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. Secondly, If to exhort; doe it with meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; It may be thou ſhalt winne more by allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, then by rigour. Thirdly, If to reproue; haue reuerence to ſuperiours, loue to equalls and inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours; but doe it <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> let them feele it ſmart; and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3120:8"/> ſo, that others alſo may feare. Enough of this, leaſt I incurre the prouerbiall ſcomme; <hi>Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Mineruam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Abſtaine from fleſhly luſts. Firſt of the obiect, <hi>Fleſhly luſts.</hi> The deſiring part of the ſoule is as the ſterne to the whole man; as the firſt moueable to the inferiour ſpheres; as the maine wheele in a clocke; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which all other faculties mooue themſelues. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections they ſay are <hi>pedes animae</hi> the ſeet of the ſoule, ſo are thoughts, intentions, actions, all thinges com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by them. Its euer the beſt or worſt part of the Soule: that ordered, all ordered; that irregular, all out of ſquare: Its that wherin piety, or profaneneſſe, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption or grace moſt ſhewes it ſelfe; that by which God moſt meaſures piety and profaneneſſe. Acts of wickedneſſe are not ſo much deteſted, as greedines of committing: Acts of obedience not ſo much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, as deſires to obey. No maruel if S. <hi>Peter</hi> be ſo deſirous to order it. From this facultie according to a threefold principle mouing it, ariſe three ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſorts of actuall deſires. Firſt Naturall, ſecondly ſpirituall, thirdly Carnall. Firſt Naturall, carrying vs from a naturall principle to things naturall in a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall manner, Secondly ſpiritual, from a ſpirituall prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple to things ſpirituall in a ſpirituall manner; or if to things naturall, yet in a ſpirituall manner. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Carnal, from a carnal principle to things carnall, or if to things natural or ſpiritual, yet in a carnal manner.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> How may we difference theſe <hi>fleſhly,</hi> from theſe naturall or ſpirituall deſires? Firſt, <hi>fleſhly</hi> deſires may thus be diſtinguiſhed from thoſe that are natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall in things of this life. They are euer immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate. So is no deſire, that is meerely naturall. <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3120:8"/> minimum petit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca;</hi> a little, neuer ſo little ſufficeth nature: moderate diet, moderate dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king; if it be but <hi>victus</hi> and <hi>veſtitus;</hi> though not <hi>victus</hi> and <hi>ornatus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> it giues to nature full contentment.</p>
                  <p>That vnmeaſurable gorging our ſelues with theſe things proceeds not from nature, but from nature depraued. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> yea <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> immoderate and ouerfre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent bibbings, to theſe not Naturall, but Carnall deſires carry vs: Immoderate heaping vp of wealth, exquiſit fineneſſe in apparrell, Epicurcall glutting our ſelues with pleaſures, is neuer deſired by right nature.<note n="a" place="margin">Prou. 30.</note> 
                     <hi>Giue me neither pouertie nor riches,</hi> is the voyce of right nature; that ſame horſleach humour, that voyce of the Graue, giue, giue, and neuer enough, iſſues from fleſh: theſe are truly <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> fleſhly deſires.</p>
                  <p>There are ſome of theſe <hi>luſts,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> ſo <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> noyſome and ſtinking, that to a man ſauouring neuer ſo little of grace, or morality, their iſſue eaſily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares to be from the fleſh. Thoſe of luxury and the daughters thereof, Heathens obſerued to flow from nature depraued; Chriſtians eaſily diſcerne not to flow from the ſpirit.</p>
                  <p>Carnall deſires are marueilous pleaſing to ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alitie,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and a kind of tickling they bring to the fleſh; and giue corruption a marueilous meaſure of Contentment: paſt queſtion it is, as the ſpirit ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors thought of things fleſhly; ſo can the fleſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in nothing but what is, as it ſelfe, corrupt and fleſhly.</p>
                  <p>As in the purſuite they are pleaſing, ſo haue they <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:3120:9"/> a farewell in bitterneſſe; after accompliſhment leaue nothing but vanity and vexation of ſpirit: How are they vaniſhed, and as a<note n="a" place="margin">Sap. 5 9.</note> poſt paſſed away? and if they leaue any thing, its a ſting. In the end they ſting as a Cockatrice, and bite as a ſerpent, as the<note n="b" place="margin">Prou. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>Harlots lips in the greeting, they drop ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe as the Hony combe, but their end is bitter as wormewood, ſharper then a two-edged ſword;</hi> as<note n="c" place="margin">Apoc. 10.</note> S. <hi>Iohns</hi> booke; <hi>ſweete as hony in the mouth, bitter as Wormewood in the bowells.</hi> They are not that make ioy and peace, the fruite of ſpirituall affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Its a Character of Carnall deſires not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned: They are vſually ſuch as are rifeſt in the multitude; who as they all lye in wickedneſſe, ſo are they carried in their deſires and delights to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what is corrupt and carnall. And if a man might meaſure goodneſſe by number, it were ſafeſt to reiect the multitude, and follow the feweſt: Chriſts flocke is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> a little diminutiue flocke. The multitude though they haue diuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of deſires, and delights, yet in this they all conſpire, to delight in nothing that good is. I am no Papiſt to meaſure truth or goodneſſe by multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; much leſſe <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> to meaſure it, by paucity of followers. Howbeit I thinke with <hi>Seneca</hi> its ordinarily true: <hi>Argumentum peſsimi turba eſt:</hi> Its a ſhrewd ſigne, the thing is none of the beſt, that is affected and applauded by the bruitiſh multitude.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> In a word; whatſoeuer deſire<note n="a" place="margin">2. Cor. 10.5.</note> exalts it ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the obedience of Chriſt, whatſoeuer is not<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 8.7.</note> ſubiect to the law of God, of it thinke its fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3120:9"/> from it fly as from a <hi>Scorpion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The act or duty followes; <hi>Abſtaine:</hi> The degrees of abſtinence thus conceiue: deſcending firſt <hi>à ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ad imum:</hi> the height of abſtinence is to repreſſe them that they ariſe not: therefore S. <hi>Paul</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 9.</note> kept his body in ſubiection; and that he might keepe it vnder, blue beate it. The meanes thus conceiue. Firſt, keepe thy minde euer buſied in ſome holy and heauenly meditation: the mind ſayth <hi>Oecume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> alwayes in action; if it be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in goodneſſe, it wanders to euill. The old ſaying is <hi>occupatum vno:</hi> the idle is tempted with two, yea with a Legion of Deuils. Secondly, Though honour may not be denyed to the body, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue it in ſtrength and vigour; yet is there a time, when macerating it almoſt may ſeeme neceſſary; That it may haue place heere, that our Sauiour ſpake; This kind of fleſhly Deuills is not caſt or kept out but by Prayer and Faſting.</p>
                  <p>A ſecond but inferior degree is, in caſe they ariſe,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> timely to repulſe them. Its ſcarce to be thought, how by a little conniuence they inſenſibly creepe vpon the minde; and incline it to allowance: The holieſt and moſt heedy cannot alwayes preuent the ariſing of euill motions; yet muſt it be our endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to repulſe them ſpeedily. We cannot hinder a bird to fly ouer our head, but may eaſily prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite her from neſtling there; fleſhly flying fancies cannot alwayes be ſuppreſſed; what thorow that <hi>morbus mentis,</hi> and what for that <hi>morſus ſerpentis</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard:</hi> Its a high point of this holy abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence to deny them harbour; to keepe our mindes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3120:10"/> from allowance, our wills from fulneſſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> It was holy aduice that <hi>Eraſmus</hi> gaue to croſſe and thwart our fleſhly inclinations; contrary what thy fleſh prouokes vnto: If Couetous deſires ariſe, haſten to a deed of liberality: If deſires of reuenge, and retaling of wrongs; doe good for euill: ſuch thwarting abates corruption; and blunts the point euen of ſatanicall temptations.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> At leaſt feed them not; eyther by meditation, or occaſion. The prudence of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> is worth our imitation, ſollicited by his Miſtris he hearkens not to her to be in her company. Our hearts are of a Gunpowder diſpoſition; a very ſparke of oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity inflames them, and ſetts all in a combuſtion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> If thy will cannot be bridled from conſenting, yet keepe thy hand from execution. Though thou couet fieldes,<note n="a" place="margin">Mic. 2.</note> take them not by force. The taſte of pleaſures of ſinne in action, encreaſeth our natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall thirſt after iniquity; one act makes not a habit; yet ſtrengthens a vitious inclination.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly; If the temptation be ſo violent that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> muſt needes vent it ſelfe into action, yet beware of fulfilling the deſires of the fleſh: Goe not ſo farre as the ſwinge of thy corrupt heart would carry thee. Its ſomething, ſaith th'apoſtle, not to obey ſinne in the luſts of it; that is, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that full meaſure that corruption would lead vs vnto. So for the Exhortation. The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons follow: firſt from our owne ſtate.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As Pilgrimes and Strangers.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.3.</note> We haue here no abiding
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3120:10"/> City; but looke for one to come: our conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, our City-freedome, our negotiation,<note place="margin">Phil 3.</note> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> is in heauen; is, or ought to be, for hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. The inference is, therefore <hi>Abſtaine from fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly luſts.</hi>
                     <note n="1" place="margin">Bernardus de quadrageſima ſer <hi>81.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Peregrinus ſi quidèm viâ regiâ incedit, non declinat ad dexteram ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad ſiniſtram: ſi fortè iur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantes viderit, non attendit: ſi nubentes aut choros ducentes, aut aliud quodlibet facientes; nihilaminus tranſit, quià peregrinus eſt, &amp; non pertinet ad eum de talibus; ad patriam ſuſpirat, ad patriam tendit; veſtitum &amp; victum habens non vult alijs onerari.</hi> In a word; they hinder vs from our home two wayes, 1. <hi>Meritoriè,</hi> 2. <hi>Effectiuè.</hi> Firſt, iuſtly by the ſentence of God hath he no portion in heauen, that preferrs in his affection, the Momentany pleaſures of ſinne, before that eternall beatitude prepared for vs in heauen Secondly, <hi>effectiuè,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Col. 3.</note> And how doe they clog, and diuert our affections from things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue? We are ſtrangers and Pilgrimes, therefore ſhould abſtaine from fleſhly luſts.</p>
                  <p>If that Reaſon ſway nothing; conſider their effect, they fight againſt the ſoule.</p>
                  <p>Its not <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, not a ſleight Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh or conflict now and than; but a continuall Warfare, and hoſtility they are in againſt the ſoule. So S. <hi>Paul</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> the law in the members <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <hi>Iames;</hi> our pleaſures, or luſts in our members <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Let vs conſider how they exerciſe it; ſee it in the weapons wherwith they aſſault vs: ſecondly in the manner of fighting.</p>
                  <p>Their weapons 1 are their Obiects 2. our inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Their obiects before enioying, After fruition.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3120:11"/> Firſt, Before enioying, as harlots gariſhly attire them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that they may draw affections; So doth fleſhly concupiſcence gariſhly adorne, and paint ouer the things deſired, that by their ſeeming beauty they may bewitch vs. The<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> tree was pleaſant to the eye, and much to be deſired for Knowledge. Proportionably ſee it in all fleſhly inclinations. Oh how glorious ſeemes wealth to a couetous eye? It is the way to reputation; the beſt proofe-armour of defence from wrongs. It brings with it an <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> A man may liue of himſelfe, yea what cannot money procure? Such a petty God ſeemes money to a couetous deſire. Ambition, how gariſh makes it honour ſeeme? When euery man muſt Cap, and Curteſie, and be at command. And ſo of the reſt.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, after fruition their fight is dangerous by the ſame weapons; as for example, what di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions breedes abundance once enioyed? Such and ſo many, that they leaue no leaſure for that <hi>vnum neceſſarium.</hi> Secondly our Inclinations: The ſeedes of all ſinnes are in all the ſonnes of <hi>Adam.</hi> Yet as in <hi>mixto</hi> when all Elements concurre; there is euer one predominant; So vſually we ſhall ſee ſome particular luſt ſwaying in euery mans ſoule; whether it be from the temper of the body, and our naturall conſtitution, or from ſome ſtrength it hath gotten in vs by ancient ill cuſtome. As Satan vſually fits temptations to our inclinations; ſo our <hi>hoſtis domeſticus,</hi> that <hi>fomes concupiſcentiae</hi> vents it ſelfe eſpecially at that channell, where its likely the victory is moſt eaſie; the recouery moſt difficult.</p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:3120:11"/>
                  <p>The manner of their warre, firſt, ſometimes <hi>ex infidijs:</hi> couertly and vnder colour of vertuous af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tells vs of<note n="a" place="margin">2 Cor.</note> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> of coloured couetouſneſſe 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> of <hi>minium virtutis;</hi> a certaine painted com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion of vertues, wherewith vices are ſometimes coloured, and take vpon them the complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of vertues: there are <hi>vitia pallitata;</hi> vices that weare the liuery of vertues, the ſword of <hi>Goliah</hi> lyes hidden vnder an <hi>Ephod,</hi> a holy garment, none to that ſayd <hi>Dauid;</hi> No ſword to <hi>Goliahs,</hi> no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice to an hypocrites; <hi>Goliahs</hi> ſword lyes hidden vnder an <hi>Ephod,</hi> the malice of hypocriſie vnder pretence of Religion: No vitious deſires are ſo inſinuatiue into well-diſpoſed natures, as theſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured, and cloaked with the ſhew of vertues. I ſhall euer preferre the ſcrupulous before the auda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and ventrous Conſcience; and thinke him ſafeſt that is ſuſpicious. <hi>Beatus qui ſemper pauidus eſt,</hi> ſayth <hi>Solomon,</hi> that is, that feares all his actions, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeakes; yea though ſtrongly vertuous.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Simulando fugam;</hi> ſuch times fall out with many <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> that they ſeeme to be quite deliuered from the power of their accuſtomed ſinnes; ſo feele they their greedineſſe in committing, it may be, through a <hi>faſtidium</hi> onely abated in them; and the motions thereof languiſhing in their hearts: Concupiſcence is ſometimes ſtupified, and therefore ſeemes morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeakes of ſome temperate for lacke of occaſions, or other abilities to exerciſe their Riot; It fares with them as with a Serpent in Winter; ſafely yee may handle them, and neede
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3120:12"/> not feare their poyſon: yet <hi>non deſunt tùm illi venena, ſed torpent:</hi> like thinke of Concupiſcence: <hi>Si vitia putas emortua, at crede mihi &amp; amputata repullulant &amp;c.</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard,</hi> They aduantage themſelues againſt vs by this retreit, as <hi>Ioſhua</hi> by his flight from the inhabitants of <hi>Ai,</hi> working ſecurity, preſumption, throwing our ſelues into occaſions of euill, laughing at temptations, as Iſrael at the Prophets Prediction. 2 <hi>Reg.</hi> 8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Laſtly <hi>aperto Marte;</hi> Its ſtrange to ſee the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prauation of mans Nature; created after Gods Image in holines, and righteouſneſſe: but now is ſo beſet with corruption, as it muſt maintaine it ſelfe againſt the Deuill with the ſword. Ah Lord, whether fell we, when we fell from thee? and thou haſt left vs in the hands of our owne counſell? no caſe, no not <hi>Sodomes</hi> ſo deſperate as when the Lord hath left vs to our ſelues.</p>
                  <p>You haue heard the nature of fleſhly luſts, 2 your duty, Abſtaine, and what it comprizeth, 3. Reaſons, firſt from your eſtate, ſecondly their effect.</p>
                  <p>Suffer now I beſeech you a little the words of exhortation.<note n="a" place="margin">1 Ioh. 2.16.</note> S. <hi>Iohn</hi> diduceth this Summary of S. <hi>Peter</hi> into three rankes: the firſt in his terme is the luſt of the fleſh; ſo fitly and by <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> hee calls thoſe of Luxury, and her daughters, ſuppoſe Drunkeneſſe, Gluttony, Laſciuiouſneſſe, Whordome. <hi>Take heede to your ſelues, leaſt at</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Luk. 21.24.</note> 
                     <hi>any time your hearts be ouercharged with ſurfetting, and Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi> Tell it not in <hi>Gath,</hi> neither publiſh it in the ſtreetes of <hi>Aſkelon;</hi> that they haue made an irrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vpon the ſonnes of the Prophets; farre be it,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3120:12"/> that they ſhould euer heare newes, that we are poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with that vncleane Deuill; that our tables ſhould ſwimme: with filthy vomitings, and the humour of drinking ſhould be taken vp amongſt the ſonnes of the Prophets: In this time of abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence at leaſt, <hi>Abſtaine from theſe fleſhly lusts, theſe fight againſt the Soule.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Oh <hi>Beſtiall Epicures</hi> they, <hi>qui Curios ſimulant, &amp; Bacchanalia viuunt,</hi> ſuffering not the force of fleſh, yet gorge themſelues with more delicious dyet: <hi>Iſay</hi> 22. <hi>Drinke wine in bowles, and ſtretch them on their beds of Iuory:</hi> And as theſe <hi>abſtemious Monkes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenti &amp; crepantes cry out, Quanta patimur;</hi> Alas indeed what torment feeles the conſcience, to giue content to a gluttonous appetite. <hi>Dearely beloued, I beſeech you as ſtrangers and pilgrimes, abſtaine from fleſhly luſts, theſe fight dangerouſly againſt the ſoule.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond is the luſt of the eye: that with <hi>Bernard</hi> is Curioſity, to others better, Couetouſneſſe; the eye is not ſatisfied with ſeeing ſaith <hi>Salomon;</hi> ſee <hi>Prou.</hi> 27 20 <hi>Eccl.</hi> 4.8. This is <hi>Senioritatis vitium: ſeniors</hi> they ſay are <hi>attenjores ad rem.</hi> Whom I know my ſoule and conſcience acquits; whom I know not I am not ſo vncharitable as to calumniate, but I could tell you of abominable ſimony among Patrons, that ſay this euill is come out from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> and they haue taken from vs the rule of practiſe; <hi>Dearely beloued, I beſeech you as pilgrims and ſtrangers abſtaine from fleshly luſts, that ſo dangerouſly fight againſt the ſoule;</hi> If they will be filthy, let them be filthy, if they will periſh, let them periſh, but <hi>ſine exemplo noſtro.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:3120:13"/>
                  <p>The laſt is pride of life; It had wont to be ſayd; <hi>they that weare ſoft raiment dwell in Kings houſes;</hi> that priuiledge of royalty our delicacy begins to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude vpon: ſo that betwixt <hi>Bethel</hi> the Kings Court, and <hi>Ramoth</hi> the ſeate of Prophets, habit makes but little diſtinction. <hi>Dearely beloued, I beſeech you as ſtrangers and pilgrimes, abſtaine from fleſhly luſts they warre, they warre dangerouſly, and that againſt the ſoule. Non eſt res parua quam ſic inſectan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur hoſtes, Ciues ſic praeſtolantur:</hi> Its a thing of no ſmall worth, that the Deuill, and fleſhly deſires ſo eagerly purſue; Saints and Angels ſo deſirouſly wiſh for, and long after.</p>
                  <closer>Deo Gloria.</closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3120:13"/>
                  <p>A SERMON Preached at TANTON in <hi>Sommerſet,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By VVILLIAM SCLATER, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour of Diuinity, and Miniſter of the word of God at <hi>Pitmiſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now publiſhed by his Sonne of Kings Colledge in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device of Thomas Harper</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by THOMAS HARPER for <hi>Robert Allot,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church yard at the ſigne of the blacke Beare. 1629.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3120:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3120:14"/>
                  <head>To the Worſhipfull M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>EDVVARD WARRE, Eſquire: And to the truly religious and right vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ELIZABETH</hi> his Wife, At <hi>Chipley</hi> in <hi>Sommerſet,</hi> my much honoured <hi>friends:</hi> Mercy and peace be multiplied.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Worſhipfull:</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>WO things more eſpeciall, haue occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned the preſent ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring of my ſeruice to you: The one is, the greatneeſſ of that loue and plenty of curteſie, which from you the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, hath euer beene deriued, and
<pb facs="tcp:3120:15"/> willingly conueyed to our familie, ſweetly to refreſh, as once the liuing, but languiſhing ſtocke, ſo now alſo all the tender branches ſprouting out from it: The other is, your vndeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued fauours towards my ſelfe in more particular. As for the firſt, we are all heires to that ſeruice, which our deare Father in all obſeruancy towards you was euer ready to performe: for the ſecond, as I more neerely ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my ſelfe to ſtand for euer obliged to you, ſo for the preſent doe deſire that my thankefull ſeruice may haue acceptance at your fauourable hands, wherein if (through want of skill to expreſſe it) I ſeeme any way defectiue, he pleaſed to ſuppoſe out of the kindneſſe of thoſe louing hearts of yours, that, that which you ſee not
<pb facs="tcp:3120:15"/> heere fully tendered by my vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned quill, is inwardly in wiſhing thoughts ſupplied: In confidence whereof, here I dedicate my ſelfe, and theſe few leaues, penned by the Author my deceaſed Father to your worthineſſe, hoping your Worſhips will vaile my boldneſſe in your good acceptance, and truſting (for the Authors ſake) that your ſtrong hands will ſupport this poſthume worke (wreſted from me by impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of ſome my reuerend, and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious friends) which can liue now by no other heat, then what your beames giues it. It flies to you as a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaued Orphan for ſhelter, confident of ſafety from the worlds vpbraiding, if you vouchſafe to yeeld it patronage. Now the God of all mercy, that hath
<pb facs="tcp:3120:16"/> ſo richly furniſhed you with his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing grace, preſerue and keepe you blameleſſe vnto the comming of the Lord Ieſus, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Worſhips in all thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full reſpectfulneſſe WILLIAM SCLATER.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From my Chamber in Kings Colledge in Cambridge.</hi>
                        <date>Nou. 18. 1628.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3120:16"/>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader; Bee pleaſed to weigh firſt in the ballance of thy more mature deliberation the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of theſe enſuing leaues, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou paſſe any cenſure on me, who, through the graue aduice of thoſe, to whoſe iudgement J ſhall euer ſubſcribe, am now the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſher of them: accept them fauourably, as they are well intended, and if thou reapeſt from them any comfort to thy conſcience, or encreaſe of thy faith, giue God the glory, and vſe it to thy greater benefit: <hi>Farewell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Thine in the Lord</hi> W. S.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3120:17"/>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:3120:17"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>2. KING. 9.31.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>Had <hi>Zimri</hi> peace that ſlue his Maſter.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the ſpeech of <hi>Iezabel,</hi> occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by the death of her ſon <hi>Iehoram;</hi> and the nigh ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch of <hi>Iehu</hi> the Miniſter of the Lords vengeance on her and her poſteritie: and tends in her intention to deterre from his bloudy, and, as to her they ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, trayterous deſignes, by remembring Gods late vengeance, on <hi>Zimri</hi> a trayterous conſpiratour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his maſter <hi>Elah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The vtterer <hi>Iezabel</hi> a monſter of her ſexe may make it queſtionable whether and how farre it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes vs for inſtruction and vſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thus conceiue 1. <hi>Omne bonum de ſuper:</hi> and <hi>omne verum aquocun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> dicatur, a Deo:</hi> All truth is of God: whoſoeuer is the vtterer, God is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour. As all light is from the Sunne, becauſe that's the <hi>primo lucidum;</hi> As all heat from fire, becauſe that is the <hi>primo calidum;</hi> ſo all truth is from God, becauſe he is the firſt truth. We may not ſay of Phariſees they might not be heard becauſe Phariſees, when they ſpeake out of <hi>Moſes</hi> chaire: Heare them, ſaid our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, though they ſay and do not. <hi>Moſes</hi> his doctrine
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3120:18"/> is of God, though a Phariſee be the publiſher: <hi>Caia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas</hi> being high Prieſt Propheſied that yeare: his Propheſie muſt not therefore be deſpiſed becauſe he was an intruder vpon the Prieſthood, and one that dipt deepe in the bloud of our Sauiour. <hi>Balaam</hi> once playd the Prophet in bleſſing Gods people, and foretelling the ſtate of the Church. We beleeue it true; God is not as Man that he ſhould lie; nor as the ſonne of man that he ſhould repent, though <hi>Balaam</hi> firſt proclaymed it. Neither will we queſtion whether God be auenger of Treaſon becauſe <hi>Iezabel</hi> makes the obſeruation. <hi>Non vitiat ſacramentum malitia miniſtrantis.</hi> Neither is the truth defiled by the polluted lips through which it paſſeth; Truth is truth whoſoeuer is the vtterer; dutie, dutie whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is our monitour; And treaſon is treaſon, odious vnto God, Though a <hi>Iezabel</hi> ſo proclames it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 The worſt mens ſpeeches and actions receiue a kinde of ſacration by their recording in holy writ: though they ſpake and did lewdly, yet the inſpirer of Scripture cauſed them holily to be recorded, and intended therein our inſtruction. Whatſoeuer was written before time, was written for our inſtruction. Vnderſtand it, not onely of the vertuous practiſes of Saints to occaſion our imitation; But of the lew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt facts of verieſt miſcreants, to be our caution. How much more thoſe holy things, thoſe pearles of wholeſome admonitions which God is pleaſed by them to caſt before vs.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. We ſay the teſtimonie of an Aduerſarie is ſtrongeſt for an Aduerſarie; we the rather beleeue ſome Theologicall truthes becauſe they haue conſent
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3120:18"/> from Heathens. In matters of morality we liſten to heathens becauſe in them the light of Nature is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued. Inceſt ſuch Inceſt is damnable, more, becauſe heathens name it not. Lying who would not more deteſt, if the deuill ſhould cry ſhame vpon it? And why is not treaſon more deteſtable, when <hi>Iezabel</hi> cries vengeance againſt it.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Her relation we finde ſuitable with Scripture ſtorie. The application after her intention ſorts with <hi>Pauls</hi> doctrinall rule: ſuch vengeances come on ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners as enſamples; And are written for our warning. Such truths according with ſacred ſtorie: ſuch ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication congruent in the generall to the Rules of Scripture, let no man deſpiſe becauſe <hi>Iezabel</hi> is the vtterer. Their congruence with Scripture makes them merit our reuerend reſpect. So farre to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent what ignorant ſcruple might pretend to ſleight the doctrine here deliuered vnto vs.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Had <hi>Zimri</hi> peace who ſlue his maſter?</head>
                     <p>THe ſtorie yee haue extant, 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 16. how <hi>Zimri</hi> Captain of halfe the Charets to <hi>Elah</hi> ſon of <hi>Baaſha,</hi> conſpired againſt him in <hi>Tirzah</hi> and ſlue him: How the people moued with indignation at the fact, create <hi>Omri</hi> Captaine of the hoſt, King ouer the ten tribes: How <hi>Zimri,</hi> whither fearing extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or madde with the croſſe of his ambition, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate through conſcience of ſuch crime, becomes an Incendiarie to himſelfe; and wilfully periſheth in the fire himſelfe had kindled in the Kings Palace.</p>
                     <p>In the Text are three things: 1. the fact of <hi>Zimri.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3120:19"/> He ſlue his Maſter.</hi> 2. The iſſue of his fact. But had <hi>Zimri</hi> peace? Did <hi>Zimri</hi> proſper? he proſperd not. 3. the application of all to <hi>Iehu</hi> intended to deterre him from ſuppoſed like ſinne, through feare of like ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance.</p>
                     <p n="1">1 The fact of <hi>Zimri Iezabel</hi> counts odious. Who but a verier ſtrumpet durſt make meritorious? How is Chriſtianitie growne more heatheniſh then hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſme it ſelfe, when ſinnes ſo monſtrous in the eye of Nature ſhall go as iuſtifiable by the word of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture?</p>
                     <p>Foorſoth: <hi>Ehud</hi> ſlue <hi>Aeglon. Anſ.</hi> True; But <hi>Aeglon</hi> a <hi>Moabite;</hi> diſabled by expreſſe law of God in regard of his Nation, to rule ouer Gods people. 2. And <hi>Ehud</hi> ſlue him: A man whom the Lord extraordinarily ſtirred vp, as <hi>Othniel,</hi> to be a deliuerer to his people: and directed by ſpeciall inſtinct to that meanes of deliuerance. I haue a word vnto thee from God O King: that <hi>verbum is factum</hi> in S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. When he ſaith he had a word from God, <hi>intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligendum eſt, hoc illi Deum vt faceret praecepiſſe:</hi> Thus vnderſtand him, that he had his warrant and precept from God to doe what he did in the manner of deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iehu</hi> ſlue <hi>Iehoram. Anſ. Iehoram,</hi> whom God the great diſpoſer of Kingdomes had depoſed from the Kingdome, and deuoted to death.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 And <hi>Iehu</hi> ſlew him, now no ſubiect to <hi>Iehoram,</hi> the annoynted King ouer <hi>Iſrael:</hi> beſides, ſent with ſpeciall commiſſion and warrant from God to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy from <hi>Ahab</hi> him that made water againſt the wall. The Prieſts oppoſe <hi>Vzziah</hi> attempting to burne
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3120:19"/> incenſe. <hi>Anſ.</hi> They inhibit his fact, draw no bloud from his perſon. Theſe and like facts warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the doers, were in great part extraordinary; ſo make vs no rule; and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> diſcrepant from thoſe now warranted to ſubiects towards their Soueraignes.</p>
                     <p>Our ordinarie rule is thus: who ſhall lay hands on the Lords annointed, and be guiltleſſe? And how waſt thou not afraid to ſtretch forth thy hand to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Lords annointed; <hi>protexit viuum, vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit mortuum,</hi> he protected him while he liued, auen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him when he was dead; ſaith S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> of <hi>Dauid</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Saul.</hi> And who that remember him that ſayd they are Gods, can thinke treaſon, bloudie trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon leſſe then higheſt ſacrilege?</p>
                     <p>It is ſayd indeed the Lord ſet <hi>Ieremie,</hi> ouer the nations and ouer the kingdomes. To roote out and pull downe; to build and to plant. <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. But S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> makes it paſt queſtion its ſpoken figuratiuely. <hi>Non quin figurata locutio tota ſit;</hi> that is, tropicallie giuen to the miniſter or proclaimer, that in propertie of ſpeech is meerelie the worke of God: As <hi>Iſay</hi> is ſent to make fat the peoples hearts, to blind their eyes, to bow downe their backes; ſo <hi>Ieremie</hi> to plucke downe kingdomes. 1. Occaſionally not <hi>efficaciter.</hi> The contempt of his miniſterie ſhould occaſion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow of ſtatelieſt kingdomes. 2. Denunciatiuelie not by way of violence. <hi>Samuel</hi> told <hi>Saul,</hi> the Lord had rent the kingdome from him: did he euer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the people to ſeditious inſurrections? <hi>Ieremie</hi> tells <hi>Zedekiah</hi> that <hi>Babilon</hi> muſt ſubdue him: But did he incourage Iewes to betray or force him to the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3120:20"/> King of <hi>Babel?</hi> God ſhall ſmite thee thou whited wall, ſayd <hi>Paul</hi> to an vſurping high Prieſt: But when he recalls his harſh terme, ſuppoſe wee he medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted perſonall violence? God ſhall ſmite him, or his day ſhall come, or he ſhall goe downe into battell and periſh: howſoeuer my hand ſhall not be vpon him. Thus <hi>Dauid,</hi> thus Ancient Saints.</p>
                     <p>Beloued we liue in wofull times, wherein morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are moſt cancelled, and too ſleightlie turned of from being bonds to conſcience. Religion euer ſince <hi>Moſes,</hi> was to be guided by a written Canon: by Popiſh diuinitie the rule of worſhip is become almoſt arbitrarie, and reſts for the moſt part in the Churches breaſt. Diſtinction of Dominions there be that thinke a meere humane policie. Prohibition of vſurie, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of Tything go current for iudicial conſtitutions? Adulterie I thinke muſt ſhortly grow a Iewiſh ſinne, murther is no longer hainous, when murther of Princes is thought meritorious.</p>
                     <p>Lord that ſuch thoughts can faſten on Chriſtian mindes inſtructed by the word of God. Moralities binding in innocencie, binde they not ſince the fall? Hath Chriſtian faith cancelled the law of Nature? Shal <hi>Iezabel</hi> cry ſhame and vengeance againſt bloudy treaſon, and we thinke the whore chaſt, that giues indulgence, propoundes heauenly rewards to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Princes? Belike then Chriſt came to deſtroy the law, not to fulfill it.</p>
                     <p>To ſay in a word, there is a tenent amongſt ſome Diuines otherwiſe orthodoxe, harſh I confeſſe to my apprehenſion: That there are caſes wherein with cautions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ubiects may beare armes againſt their ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3120:20"/> I am loth to procure their enuie, knowing their paines otherwiſe reuerend in the Church of God. There is, I know, wide difference betwixt <hi>princeps factus</hi> and <hi>princeps natus.</hi> They ſay (them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues muſt defend it), It is <hi>eiuſdem tollere cuius po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere,</hi> where the Prince is but factious. But this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion I hope we all hold firme; Where immediate prouidence ſettles kingdomes, no other but Gods immediate hand may attempt to ouerthrow them. But out vpon that deuilitie taught in Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> without diſtinction warranting to ſubiects murther of their Naturall Princes, be pretenſes what they may be.</p>
                     <p>Suppoſe them Tyrants by abuſe of power, was not <hi>Saul</hi> ſuch? yet who may lay hand on him, and be guiltleſſe? Suppoſe by vſurpation, was not <hi>Baaſha</hi> ſuch? continued not <hi>Elah</hi> that intruſion? yet <hi>Zimri</hi> had no peace that ſlue him.</p>
                     <p>Suppoſe them Heretikes. Is hereſie groſſer crime then Idolatrie? <hi>Elah</hi> was an Idolater. It is truely ſaid, <hi>factum ſine errore non facit haereticum:</hi> Hereſie im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports errours in iudgement. Yet may facts implie hereſie, when the ground of doing is heretically erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous. The fact of the Idolater is not hereſie: but his opinion, the ground of his fact, may gather him into the ranke of heretikes. To inuocate deuils is in the fact no hereſie, though damned impietie. But the opinion of deitie or adorableneſſe to dwell in Deuils is groſſeſt hereſie. The fact of the fornicatour is not hereſie, but beaſtly luxurie; But the opinion of <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi> that fornication is <hi>res media,</hi> is damned hereſie. To wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God in an Image is not in the fact hereticall; yet
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3120:21"/> opinion that God is acceptably worſhipped in an Image, what is it leſſe then hereſie? Suppoſe them therefore Tyrants, ſuppoſe them Heretikes; yet what peace may the Traytour looke for more then <hi>Zimri</hi> that ſlew his maſter, tyrannous and no leſſe then He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall?</p>
                     <p>And muſt <hi>Rome</hi> hatching ſuch monſters of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, be ſtill reputed the Church, the only Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like vpon earth out of which is no ſaluation? The Church ſo infallibly lead by the Spirit into all truth that ſhe cannot poſſible be erroneous in her dogma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall reſolutions?</p>
                     <p>By their fruites yee ſhall know them; that is by their Doctrines. For theſe are fruites of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets as Prophets. Legitimate they notorious brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the morall Law? How are they the Church of God? wil worſhip, Image worſhip they teach ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God though damned in the ſecond pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept: Equiuocating in oathes, that is, couert periurie, they iuſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fie againſt the third precept. Diſhonour of Parents for religion ſake, murther of Princes they make <hi>in caſu</hi> meritorious.</p>
                     <p>Curſed be ſuch faith, it's helliſh; ſuch practiſe, it's no leſſe then Deuiliſh, methinkes we ſhould now reſolue &amp; ſay with <hi>Iacob;</hi> Into their ſecret let not my ſoule come: my glory be not thou ioyned with their aſſemblie. So of the fact of <hi>Iehu;</hi> his iſſue followes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Had Zimri peace?</hi> Did <hi>Zimri</hi> proſper? he proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not. Seuen dayes onely he reigned in <hi>Tirzah:</hi> and becomes a deſperate incendiarie to himſelfe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Zimri</hi> had no peace: muſt therefore his fact be thought vnlawfull? Beſt actions haue ſometimes
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3120:21"/> their Croſſes: lewdeſt attempts proſperous ſucceſſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> Goodneſſe or euilneſſe of humane actions no man wiſely meaſures by the diſpoſitions of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence; But by their diſſonance or congruitie to the Law of God. Precept and prohibition are the primarie rule of good and euill. Prohibition makes euill, euill: vengeance ſhewes it euill, and odious vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God. The murther of Princes law Naturall and morall make euill: when vengeance ouertakes the traytour, that ſhewes it hatefull to God, and warnes vs to fly it, if not for Conſcience, yet for feare of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance. 2. And the diſtinction is ancient, there is <hi>poena vindictae</hi> and there is <hi>poena caſtigationis</hi> or <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bationis;</hi> Croſſes that come in the way of tryalls, at no hand argue our actions euill. The building of the Temple vnder <hi>Ezra</hi> we finde diſappointed by the people of the Land; yet was their attempt holy and acceptable vnto God. The croſſe comes to proue their faith; to try their dependance on God. But puniſhments that come in the Nature of vengeances are apparent euidences that the attempts are euill. Such this of <hi>Zimri.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Had Zimri peace?</hi> Why not? when he fulfills the Prophets prediction, executes Gods will in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying <hi>Baaſha</hi> his poſteritie; A prophecie went before of <hi>Baaſha</hi> that his familie ſhould be put out in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Becauſe he had walked in the way of <hi>Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi> and made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſin, his houſe muſt be like that of <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> his poſteritie vtterly deſtroyed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thus yee may Anſwer-Prediction there was of <hi>Baaſhaes</hi> deſtruction; Preſcript none to <hi>Zimri</hi> to be the executioner, There be that ſay: <hi>Praeſcit
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3120:22"/> Deus mala, non praeordinat.</hi> God foreknowes and foretels euils, preordaines them not; Its true, <hi>quà mala.</hi> Yet may we not imagine our God an idle ſpectatour of the malice of men. His preſcience euen of euill preſuppoſeth ſome act of his will, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining to permit them.</p>
                     <p>But thus thinke; there is wide difference betwixt the inſtruments of Gods prouidence, and the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of his ordinance, thoſe fulfill his purpoſes; theſe alſo doe his commandes. <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> and the Elders of the people, did what Gods hand and ſecret counſell determined ſhould be done in the death of our bleſſed Sauiour; yet iuſtly falls Gods wrath vpon them: they were vnwitting in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of his prouidence, no Miniſters of his ordinance. When <hi>Iehu</hi> deſtroyed the poſteritie of <hi>Achab:</hi> he ſinned not in the fact; beſides predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Prophet, he had his ſpeciall commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from God; wherefore alſo his fact is crowned as obedience, and rewarded with the Kingdomes continuance in his poſteritie vnto foure generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. When <hi>Zimri</hi> ſlue <hi>Elah</hi> there was like predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but no ſuch commiſſion; therefore <hi>Zimri</hi> had no peace that ſlue his maſter.</p>
                     <p>Briefly, firſt Gods ſecret appointments are not the rule of our Actions but his reueled precepts. Doe what God preſcribes, thou ſinneſt not but art accepted with him; though perhaps in the iſſue thou croſſe his ſecret determinations. Violate his precepts, though thou fulfil his ſecret appointments, thou art obnoxious to the wrath of God. It's poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> for a man <hi>bona voluntate velle
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3120:22"/> quod Deus non vult,</hi> as when a pious child deſires and prayes for his fathers life whom God hath deſigned to death. And a man may <hi>malâ volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate velle quod Deus vult bonâ?</hi> a man may irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly will that which God alſo willes: ſuppoſe when an vngratious ſonne deſires the death of his father, which God alſo willeth. The one willes what God willes not, the other wills what God alſo wills, and the ones pietie is more conſonant to the good will of God, though willing another thing; then the others impietie, willing the ſame that God hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined in his ſecret counſell. So much auailes it to limit our ſelues to Gods reuealed precept.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 Beſides <hi>in hoc examine,</hi> in tryall of ſuch actions the inquirie is not <hi>quid fecerint,</hi> but <hi>quid voluerint;</hi> not what they did, but what they intended; And <hi>in rationem venit, non factum,</hi> but <hi>conſilium et vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas,</hi> not ſo much their fact, as their purpoſe and intention in doing. God intended and diſpoſed the vnnatural crueltie of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Brethren to good; yet they thought euill; therefore felt the ſmart of famine, feare of bondage, and the ſtroke of Conſcience; And who ſo forlorne or impudent amongſt miſcreants to ſay, that in his damned ambition, or Couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or luxurie, he had reſpect to the will of God which no man lightlie knowes but by the euent. <hi>Aſhur</hi> is the rod of Gods wrath: by him the Lord accompliſheth his worke vpon Ieruſalem; yet will he viſit the proud heart of the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> and bring downe his haughtie and proud lookes; the equitie is apparent: He thinketh not ſo; but it is in his heart to deſtroy and cut off Nations; to ſatiate
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3120:23"/> his infinite ambition, curſed couetouſneſſe and pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous luxurie.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 Generalities of Gods purpoſe to deſtroy <hi>Baaſha</hi> his poſterity we will ſuppoſe made knowne to <hi>Zimri;</hi> that intellignce he might haue by the Prophets pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction: But particulars of the meanes, as that hee ſhould be the Agent God reueled not, though there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he did what God determined, yet had he no peace in ſlaying his Maſter. So poſſible is it to doe what God determines, and yet to be obnoxious to his wrath I would to God it were ſeriouſly medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted amongſt our people; that the multitude were not ſtill tranſported with that fury of Atheiſme; to think ſinnes excuſable, their ſinnes no ſinnes becauſe they ſort in the euent with the ſecret appointments of Gods counſell: Generally yee may obſerue ſinnes fathered vpon prouidence, which are damned in Gods word and haue no other cauſe but the malice of the committers. Fate and fortune Chriſtians hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſhly cry out of; and God made Authour of that whereof he is <hi>vltor.</hi> Theeues and murtherers and bloudy Traytours, when vengeance ſeizeth on them, blame deſtinie or Planets or harder fortune, as well their ſinnes as their vengeance are reſolued to God as to their firſt Cauſe. Yet <hi>Dauid</hi> taught vs, that God is not a God that willeth iniquitie: And S. <hi>Iames,</hi> God cannot be tempted with euill, neither tempteth he any man. Our Sauiour points vs to the trueſt fountaine of all vitious euills; Out of the heart come Adulteries, murthers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thefts blaſphemies or if there be any thing elſe that naught is. And <hi>Iames;</hi> Euery man is tempted of his owne concupiſcence
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3120:23"/> being thereby drawne away and intiſed.</p>
                     <p>And though it be true God hath his action euen in euill, his action I meane as <hi>Dameſcene.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> by way of permiſſion, yet workes he not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in by way of impreſſion or inclination. He deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines to permit the ſinner to the Swinge of his owne corrupt heart, to ſuffer his doing of that euill whereto he is ſelfely inclined, and to order it to his Glory. Neither may any quarell that he reſtraines or reformes not. Firſt God is <hi>Agens liberrimum,</hi> not bound to his creature<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſecondly, &amp; bonds he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs ſufficient to reſtraine from euill. Firſt, His law, ſecondly, his threatened vengeance, thirdly our own Conſcience. A threefold Cord is not eaſily broken: yet the vitious heart of man findes meanes enough to breake theſe bonds aſunder, to caſt away theſe Cords from them. And which paſſeth all meaſure of impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie looke if not for recompenſe from God, yet for excuſe with him, becauſe they fulfilled his ſecret appointments. <hi>Had Zimri peace that ſlue his Maſter?</hi> yet accompliſhed he the ſecret appointment of God. Actions are neuer regular till they ſute with Precept, howſoeuer congruent they may be to Gods ſecret ordinance.</p>
                     <p>The application of all to <hi>Iehu,</hi> remaines. Let <hi>Iehu</hi> therfore beware like Trayterous attempts, leaſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily he taſt like vengeance of God.</p>
                     <p>How followes the Argument from one particular to another, from one inſtance to the generalitie of murtherous Traytors. Muſt <hi>Iehu,</hi> all Traitours expect ſo dreadfull death, becauſe ſuch was <hi>Zimries</hi> fate? Behold how many miſcreants ſee we proſper in euill,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3120:24"/> how rare are examples of Gods viſible vengeance?</p>
                     <p>At this ſtone how many ſoules ſtumble, how many haue ſo ſtumbled that they haue fallen into the neathermoſt Hell. To ſee Gods patient for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance of many in like ſinnes, ſo rare particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars culled out to be enſamples. Confeſſedly won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull is Gods patience: his tolerance great of many veſſels of wrath prepared to deſtruction. Diuines giue reaſons of it.</p>
                     <p>Therefore, ſaith <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſome are here puniſhed that we may know there is a prouidence taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of all; Therefore not all, that we may beleeue there is a iudgement to come.</p>
                     <p>And haue we not ſeene worſt men become Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of holieſt Children? That <hi>Ahaz</hi> matchleſſe for impietie, was father yet to good <hi>Hezekiah.</hi> And out of <hi>Ammon</hi> a reuolt from his fathers pietie iſſued <hi>Ioſiah</hi> peereleſſe for piety amongſt the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iudah.</hi> Pregnancie after humane equitie reſpits the death of the moſt notorious amongſt women. Iuſtice wiſely conſiders; it ſauours much of iniurie to make the innocent Infant abortiue for the ſinne of the mother; and hopefully preſumes the childe may be inſtrument of good to the common-wealth, if mans forbearance on ſuch occaſions be thought ſutable to Iuſtice; why not Gods much more, to like intentions.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 There is an height and full meaſure of ſinning whereto prouidence will haue miſcreants aſcend, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the laſt vengeance ſweepes them away; fill vp the meaſure of your iniquitie, ſayd our Sauiour to <hi>Iewes,</hi> that on you may come the bloud of Prophets, the wickedneſſe of Amorites is not yet full,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3120:24"/> therefore their vengeance hath foure hundred yeares reſpit. Yet what if we ſay no man ſinnes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his vengeance, there is inſeparably accident to the tranſient act of ſinne a threefold miſchiefe. 1. <hi>Macula.</hi> 2. <hi>Reatus.</hi> 3. <hi>Poena.</hi> the ſtaine, the guilt and the puniſhment properlie ſo called, yet the ſtaine and guilt haue in them penaltie. Firſt, The ſoule is ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed, the eximious pulchritude thereof defiled. Secondly, Conſcience trembles at the guilt and obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to puniſhment before other extremities fall vpon the ſenſe, ſo that <hi>Plutarchs</hi> obſeruation was as true as elegant: As malefactours in the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, had this as part of their puniſhment, to beare their Croſſe to the place of execution, ſo beares euery ſinner his Croſſe, his torture, while he is but in <hi>viâ ad extremum ſupplicium.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Laſtly as in bleſſings promiſed to obedience God ſometimes deales by way of exchange, ſo in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, exchanging bodily for ſpirituall: inſteed of death, or famine or the ſword, ſends horrour of Conſcience and aſtoniſhment of heart, ſo that they become as <hi>Paſhur</hi> terrors and no leſſe then burthens to themſelues: or obſtinacie of will, and hardneſſe of heart that they may neuer repent but be eternally damned that had pleaſure in vnrighteouſneſſe.</p>
                     <p>But to the point.</p>
                     <p>Firſt the old ſaying is, what betides any one, may befall euery one. Let all ſinners tremble at any ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners vengeance. It may be their fate that hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallen another. Secondly, the Argument well followes from a particular to the generalitie, where is like rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of all. The cauſe of vengeance is alike in al; And in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3120:25"/> ſuch ſingulars, for the paritie of the ſinne may well be expected equalitie of vengeance. So farre there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the inference is current.</p>
                     <p>Yet its true<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> her application is erroneous to the perſon of <hi>Iehu. Iehu</hi> is not as <hi>Zimri</hi> a ſubiect, but now an annoyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed King; Gods ſelected miniſter to take vengeance of the houſe of <hi>Achab;</hi> comes with commiſſion from the great Lawgiuer to this ſeeming breach of the generall precept: his fact is not as <hi>Zimries,</hi> treaſon, but obedience, in reſpect of the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all warrant and command of God giuen vnto him.</p>
                     <p>Ly diſpenſations or exemptions in matters of this Nature? that is a queſtion which popiſh ſpirits ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily on any occaſion apprehend; and are readie to inferre that as the great Lawgiuer to <hi>Ehud</hi> and <hi>Iehu;</hi> ſo his vice-gerent on earth may giue indulgence and diſpenſation in ſuch moralities.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> It hath anciently bin queſtioned in Schooles whether morall precepts be diſpenſable by authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of God himſelfe: and was neuer but with cautio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate diſtinction affirmed. But that man ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe with Gods morall commandes hath rarely bin diſputed; neuer till of late by any determined. The greateſt flatterers of Popiſh pride and ambition an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently thus reſolued. <hi>Papa etſi ſit ſuper omne Ius purè poſitivum,</hi> yet is he not <hi>ſuper Ius Naturae aut diuinum.</hi> The Pope though he be aboue all Law meerely poſitiue, yet is he at no hand ſuperiour to the Law of God or Nature. And iudge in your ſelues, firſt, can man looſe Conſcience where God hath bound it? ſecondly, Or ſtands fraile man on euen termes with the Almighty to equall or affront
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3120:25"/> him in Authoritie. Where are theſe records extant wherin God hath conueied ſuch Authoritie to man to legitimate what he hath condemned? Poore ſoules miſerably infatuated they muſt needs be, that thinke Gods royalties, his peculiar prerogatiues communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable to his creature.</p>
                     <p>Yeeld it for the preſent the trueſt Etymon of the Popes Epithete: <hi>Antichriſtus, quaſi vice Chriſtus:</hi> a vice-Chriſt, his vice-gerent and Vicar generall on earth: Receiues the ſurrogate by his ſubſtitution, power more then was congruent to the principall?</p>
                     <p>A threefold power of Chriſt their owne diuines obſerue in this queſtion. Firſt one diuine and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, belonging to our mediatour Ieſus, as the ſonne of God, God equall to his father. Hereto belongs originally, the diſpoſing of kingdomes; the making or antiquating of lawes; and diſpenſing with them. Secondly, Another meerly ſpiritual, congruent to the man Chriſt, but as they ſpeake to him as a man im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall and glorious now managed by himſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out deputie at the right hand of his father. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, A third which he had and exerciſed by him as a mortall man in the dayes of his fleſh. Wherin alone, as themſelues confeſſe, the Pope may lay claime to his ſubſtitution, as being the only poſſible for meere man to manage. See if euer our Sauiour admitted or exerciſed ſuch Regalitie on earth: Aſſumed ſuch do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, power ſo eximious as to diſpoſe of crownes, to tranſlate Kingdomes: Authoritie ſo tranſcendent, as to cancell the lawes of God, or to Legitimate high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt breaches of morall precepts. Heare him ſpeaking to the firſt: Oh <hi>homo quis me conſtituit Iudicem aut
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3120:26"/> diuiſorem inter vos?</hi> Man who hath made me a iudge or diuider betwixt you? And to <hi>Pilate</hi> his profeſſion is; His kingdome is not of this world. To the ſecond; he came not to deſtroy the law, but to fulfill it.</p>
                     <p>See his next ſucceſſours as thy are ſtiled, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; euer medled they with ſuch altitudes of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralitie? Aſſumed they ſuch Authoritie? <hi>Stetiſſe lego Apoſtolos judicandos; ſediſſe iudicantes non lego, Erit illud, non fuit;</hi> ſayd <hi>Bernard</hi> elegantly to Pope <hi>Eugenius</hi> interpoſing himſelfe as Iudge in ciuill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions; that the Apoſtles ſtood to be iudged I read; that they ſate as Iudges I read not. That ſhalbe their glorie in the Regeneration, to ſit on Thrones iudging the twelue tribes of Iſrael. Such magnificence they aſpired to none in the dayes of their mortalitie. Only to the Biſhop of Rome, to that <hi>ſeruus ſeruorum Dei,</hi> belongs equalitie of power with God himſelfe: As, God ſo may he authorize violations of morall precepts and diſpenſe euen with the lawes of God, As God to <hi>Iehu</hi> to ſlay <hi>Iehoram,</hi> to <hi>Ehud</hi> to ſlay <hi>Eglon,</hi> ſo this <hi>Deus Deorum</hi> giue indulgence to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects to murther their Naturall princes. But enough of that Arrogancie no leſſe then <hi>Luciferian:</hi> we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to <hi>Iezabel</hi> her miſ application.</p>
                     <p>Here muſt be acknowledged the miſtake and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of <hi>Iezabel,</hi> her miſ-application to the perſon of <hi>Iehu. Iehu</hi> is not, as <hi>Zimri,</hi> led with priuate ambition, but comes with Authority from God to deſtroy <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horam,</hi> and his Brethren. To him therefore imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently is that example of Gods vengeance. Howbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, after her hypotheſis, her obſeruation and caution
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3120:26"/> is good; ſuppoſing <hi>Iehu</hi> as <hi>Zimri</hi> a trayterous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiratour againſt his maſter, <hi>Zimries</hi> vengeance ſhould haue bin <hi>Iehu</hi> his warning.</p>
                     <p>Sure it is, Gods vengeances are exemplarie; And ſhould be warnings to all, to flie like ſinnes, leaſt they taſt like vengeance. So Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hauing to <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> reckoned vp a catalogue of Iſraelites ſinnes, and related their vengeance, admoniſheth, that they came to them as enſamples, and were written for our warning on whom the ends of the world are come. So Saint <hi>Peter</hi> mentioning the fall of Angels, the fearefull ouerthrow of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> and the deluge brought vpon the old world, cloſeth that they were ſet forth as Enſamples.</p>
                     <p>Thus haue Saints holily vſed their meditation. <hi>Nehemiah</hi> obſeruing <hi>Sabbathes</hi> polluted in Ieruſalem, thus to the Rulers. Did not our fathers thus, and all this wrath came vpon vs? In another particular: fell not <hi>Salomon</hi> by this meanes, though beloued of his God?</p>
                     <p>The Ambaſſadours from the Congregation, to the <hi>Rubenites, Gadites</hi> and halfe Tribe of <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> erecting an Altar not for ſacrifice as was ſuppoſed, but for memoriall, yet in ſuſpicion of ſuch euill, would thus deterre them. Is the iniquitie of <hi>Peor</hi> too little from which we are not clenſed vnto this day, that you muſt returne alſo from following the Lord? why am I long.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, Gods Iuſtice we know to be impartiall, with God there is no reſpect of Perſons. Secondly, And they muſt looke to partake in the plagues that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take in the ſinnes of Babylon.</p>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:3120:27"/>
                     <p>I can wiſh on this occaſion as <hi>Moſes,</hi> Oh that Gods people were wiſe: ſo wiſe as to thinke euerie ſinners vengeance exemplarie; and to make it their warning how they fall by example of like diſobedience. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence neuer ſo ſlept but it hath affoorded to all ages ſpectacles of Gods wrath, examples of his ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance vpon the children of diſobedience. Drunkards how many haue we ſeene after <hi>Salomons</hi> threatening, cloathed with rags: Adulterers filled with rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; brought to a morſell of bread: louers of paſtime &amp; ſporting brought to pouertie. Honourable families ruined by harbouring Popiſh ſuperſtition, expoſed to Gods wrath by oppreſſion of the poore, by their exceſſe of Ryot, and luxurious intemperance. Yet who when he ſees this, feares and learnes to doe no more preſumptuouſly? And rather thinkes not as the Hypocrites in <hi>Iſai.</hi> Though a Plague run ouer all, it ſhall not come nigh him? And is not readie to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit ſome ſingular ſpecialtie in their degree and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of ſinning whom vengeance hath ſo ouertaken?</p>
                     <p>To ſpeake to the particular in hand: how frequent haue bin examples of Gods vengeance vpon bloudie traitours? Who hath euer knowne bloudie traitour to haue dyed a dry death? <hi>Had Zimri peace that ſlew his Maſter?</hi> Had <hi>Gowrie</hi> peace that attempted to ſlay his Maſter? Went thoſe incendiaries of the Powder-treaſon without bloud to their Graues? I had almoſt ſayd to their Hell. Search records diuine, humane, and ſay who euer proſpered that but dipped his finger in the bloud of the Lords annoynted. It is very remarkeable in this ſinne more then in many; Though vengeance hath paſſed ouer other ſinners, yet ſeldome miſſed it the head of a bloudy traitour.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3120:27"/> Blaſphemers and Atheiſts we haue ſeene liuing and dying without any viſible vengeance: Murtherers ſome to haue gone to their Graues in peace: Bloudy traytors few or none that haue eſcaped the hand of God, or ſword of the Magiſtrate.</p>
                     <p>Yea ſingular ſpecialties there are many obſeruable in their vengeance: Many dying in the fact, in the heat of purſuing their ambitious and trayterous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes: ſo died <hi>Zeba</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Bichri:</hi> ſo <hi>Abſolon</hi> in the heat of his parricidious ambition, partly by the hand of God, partly by the ſword of <hi>Ioab.</hi> Oh <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon my ſonne, my ſonne Abſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lon would God I had dyed for thee,</hi> ſayth <hi>Dauid</hi> conſidering the likely iſſues of ſuch death ſo inflicted. What meanes lamen ation ſo comfortleſſe and immoderate in <hi>Dauid</hi> ouer an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratious <hi>Abſolon.</hi> We erre in S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> Iudgement, if we thinke <hi>Dauid</hi> ſo <hi>Rachel-like</hi> weeped for loſſe of his Childe though deare vnto him. <hi>Non orbitatem do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luit</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin:</hi> It was not his own orbitie which <hi>Dauid</hi> ſo lamentablie bewayled, but ſeeing into what torments a ſoule ſo impiouſly adulterous, ſo vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally trayterous and parricidious, eſpecially ſo cut off by the hand of God, ſhould now in all likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods be plunged. And ſurely whateuer our ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Charitie may conceit, they are miſerable deaths that ſeize on ſinners in the heat of their ſinnes.</p>
                     <p>Yea ſee in <hi>Zimries</hi> vengeance ſomething more to be trembled at. God giues him vp to become his owne deaths man. Neither was that <hi>Zimri</hi> his fate only, thus dyed the traytour <hi>Iudas,</hi> thus <hi>Achitophel,</hi> thus <hi>Abimelech;</hi> Thus ſome of trayterous deſignes in our owne remembrance. It is ſayd indeed God may haue
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3120:28"/> mercie <hi>inter pontem &amp; fontem,</hi> betwixt the Bridge and the Brooke. I limit not Gods mercie to times. Howbeit S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> long ſince determined of the fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt pretenſes brought for ſelfe-murther, they cannot all excuſe it from being mortall ſinne. But when a man from his Cradle nuzled in Popiſh ſuperſtition, proceedes at laſt to a ſinne ſo haynous as is murther of Princes, and makes cloſe of his owne life in ſelfe-murther, my charitie cannot be ſo charitable as to hope of that mans ſaluation.</p>
                     <p>Such haue bin the iſſues of many traytours. They befell them as enſamples for our Caution and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Yet when may we hope for more loyaltie from ſeduced amongſt Papiſts. A <hi>Hydra</hi> of treaſon there ſeemes to be amongſt them; after ſo many hands of bloudy traytours cut off, ſpring vp new continually of like trayterous braines; God grant our too much indulgence multiply not that ſeed of the wicked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs. Truly ſayd S. <hi>Iohn</hi> of that wine of Popiſh fornication, it is <hi>vinum inebrians,</hi> wine that makes drunke. It is not <hi>vinum</hi> but <hi>venenum</hi> and <hi>toxicum;</hi> ſo <hi>intoxicates,</hi> ſo <hi>infatuates</hi> it vnto madneſſe thoſe that drinke deepe of the dreg thereof; If there be any of that hereſie which here me this day, I aduiſe them not to ſlight the notice of ſuch vengeances, and pray God for them they may be their Caution.</p>
                     <p>To others hitherto of more loyall diſpoſition may it ſerue to increaſe abhorrence from ſinnes ſo mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous. Euen for our warning is ſuch vengeance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted; And ſhould increaſe deteſtation of ſins, from which conſcience by light of nature or Grace is moſt abhorrent. How dyed <hi>Zimri,</hi> how <hi>Iudas,</hi> how <hi>Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel?</hi>
                        <pb n="39" facs="tcp:3120:28"/> Their owne hands made paſſage for their ſoules into helliſh torments, as the deuill once com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained before their time. How dyed <hi>Abſolon,</hi> how <hi>Zebah</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Bichri,</hi> how <hi>Gowrie,</hi> how the incendiary traytours. All by the hand of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, moſt in the heat of their ſinne. Thus they peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed to become our warnings.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sic perierunt.</hi> And I pray as <hi>Deborah</hi> and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude: <hi>Sic pereant inimici tui Domine.</hi> So let all thine enemies periſh O Lord, but let them that loue thee, let thine annoynted be as the Sunne when he riſeth in his might. Binde vp his ſoule in the bundle of life. Strike through the Loynes of them that riſe vp againſt him, that hate him, that they neuer riſe vp againe. Heare vs O Lord and anſwer vs; for thy Names ſake, for thy Chriſt his ſake in whom we know thou art well pleaſed. To whom with thee O father and thy bleſſed Spirit, for all thy mercies for thy gracious protection and deliuerances of our King and State, be aſcribed and giuen of vs and of thy whole Church, All Prayſes, Power, Maieſtie, Dominion and thankeſgiuing, henceforth and for euer <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <closer>Deo Gloria.</closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3120:29"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3120:29"/>
                  <p>A FVNERALL SERMON Preached at the Buriall of the Right Worſhipfull M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. IOHN COLLES Eſquier, one of his Maieſties Iuſtices of Peace and Quorum in <hi>Sommerſetſhire</hi> Anno. Dom. 1607.</p>
                  <p>By WILLIAM SCLATER, of Kings Colledge in <hi>Cambridge</hi> Miniſter of Gods Word at <hi>Pitmiſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device of Thomas Harper</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by THOMAS HARPER for <hi>Robert Allot,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Churchyard at the ſigne of the Black Beare. 1629.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3120:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3120:30"/>
                  <head>To the Worſhipfull M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>GEORGE COLLES, Eſquire:</hi> Mercy and peace be multiplied.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir:</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Heere preſent you with a Sermon, whoſe concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, birth and being, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from your renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Father, as from the ſweet influence of a bright ſhining ſtar in the celeſtiall Orbe, on which the eyes of all vertuouſly diſpoſed were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer firmely fixed, euen to admiration; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it being now brought foorth, ſues for ſafe protection vnder you his Sonne, and hopes to receiue fauourable acceptance from you, being the knowne patron to goodneſſe. Tis the paucity of ſuch, which makes glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:3120:31"/> vice ſo audaciouſly impudent as to dare giue affront to baſhfull vertue, that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes inglorious. If any encreaſe of heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowledge and celeſtiall comfort may accrew to your ſoule from it, giue God the prayſe, and the Authour is ſatisfied. So with my prayers to God for continuance, and multiplication of heauenly and earthly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings vpon you, I reſt</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your hearty well-willer WILLIAM SCLATER.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From my Chamber in Kings Colledge in Cambridge.</hi>
                        <date>Nou. 18. 1628.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3120:31"/>
                  <head>The Preface.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloued in Chriſt Ieſus, we are met together this day to performe the laſt office and duty of Charity to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian brother, an aged and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend gentleman, a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate of eminent and beſt place amongſt vs. And though I know the principall end of ſuch ſermons be the inſtruction of the liuing; yet I take it there is a lawfull and warrantable commemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the vertues, and deſerued praiſes of the dead, as well to ſtirre vp to praiſe God for his graces that ſhined in them, as to prouoke others to imitate their holy example. Concerning this worſhipfull Gentleman deceaſed, theſe thinges I can ſpeake neither for faſhion, nor for flattery. For Religion, the principall commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all men, of meaner, or higher place in the world, this teſtimony we can all giue him;
<pb facs="tcp:3120:32"/> that he was an ancient, and conſtant profeſſor of the truth, now taught and maintained in this Church of England; yea a man delighted in the title of a profeſſour of the ſtricteſt ſort; a thing that moſt great ones throw of with that odious nickname of Puritaniſme. For loue of this truth theſe worthy euidences he gaue of it, while health laſted, an ordinary, attentiue, delightfull, and, as I perſwade my ſelfe, a profitable hearer. In this kind that one thing is eminent, his care to furniſh this place where himſelfe was an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary hearer, with a Miniſter of ſome compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ability to inſtruct the people, and free from ſcandall in life. And herein how free he was from all Simoniacall practiſes, my ſelfe am a thankefull witneſſe; and the ſame teſtimonie can many others giue him touching my predeceſſor whoſe ſoule is now with God, a rare and worthy example. And if ſuch vertues were capable of bequeathment, I could wiſh he had left this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable part amongſt others for a Legacy to men in his ſort; to ſee the cunning couetous dealing of moſt men in this kind it is lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſuch reſeruations and annuall gratuities, ſuch curtolling of Miniſters maintenance, as
<pb facs="tcp:3120:32"/> 
                     <hi>Hanun</hi> vſed the garments of <hi>Dauids</hi> ſeruants, they are cut off by the middle. And <hi>Michas</hi> his wages, ten ſhekells of ſiluer, a liuery, and meate and drinke, a large allowance for a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and indeed fit maintenance for ſuch Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines, but yet a filthy practiſe in ſuch Patrons. For practiſe of life, ſubiect to frailties, and who is free? But for aught I know cleare from noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious crimes; If any haue beene ſo credulous as to cenſure him vpon bare rumour, let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that ſuch credulity agrees not with charity, and let him feare, leaſt the hard mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures he hath mete vnto this gentleman, be no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> rendred him double in Gods iuſt iudgement. For ſtate and calling, a Magiſtrate of higheſt place amongſt vs; employed in affaires of weightieſt importance; a good argument of his tryed fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity: For loue of his Country conſpicuous; for diſpatch of buſineſſe ſpeedy, and painefull, yea euen in time of weakeneſſe: And as I haue heard, bewailing his weakeneſſe for noe one thing more, then that it diſabled him for ſeruice of the Country. Come we to behauiour in ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, it pleaſed God to afflict him with a long, violent and painefull diſeaſe; yet this hath bin
<pb facs="tcp:3120:33"/> obſerued in him, that he neuer vttered any one ſpeech of impatience, and diſcontentment at the hand of God. So great patience vnder ſo great afflictions argues (me thinkes) ſome apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Gods loue euen in afflictions. And that we might ſee his conſtancy in loue of the truth, when God had debarred him from the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, be was not onely willing, but deſirous to heare in priuate; often melting into teares, as well at the propounding of Gods ſweete mercies, as at reproofes and denuntiations of iudgements. In priuate conference deſirous and glad to be farther informed touching his owne eſtate, and meanes of Saluation, anſwering with teares to moſt things propounded; to me a good argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>argument of a contrite heart, which God hath promiſed not to deſpiſe. In the laſt agony ſo long as God gaue memory often calling on that ſweete name of Ieſu for helpe, mercy, pardon of ſinnes. Yet when ſome diſtractions were on him through violence of paines, able and ready to giue a reaſon of his hope, being demanded of the ground of his hope of Saluation he profeſſed to cleaue only to the merits of Chriſt: demanded againe a reaſon of his hope to haue part in
<pb facs="tcp:3120:33"/> Chriſts merits; he thus anſwered; becauſe I ſeeke him: and ſurely, ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi> thou Lord neuer faileſt them that ſeeke thee in ſincerity. Yea after vſe of outward ſenſes was gone, we often heard paſsionate callings on the name of Ieſu (I doubt not but he found ſweetneſſe in that name) to help him, and haue mercy on him. Theſe ſo many, and ſo worthy preſcriptions, methinkes muſt needes wring from the moſt vncharitable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs at least a hopefull perſwaſion that he dyed Gods Child. And for mine owne part I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but profeſſe more then a hope that his ſoule is with God. If any man thinke I haue beene too prodigall of his prayſes, let him thus iudge, that Chriſtian charity as it loues not to tenter the ſins of others, but euer to extenuate human fraileties, ſo is it delighted to amplifie to the vtmost the iuſt praiſes of them it reſpects. Yet this withall; if I haue any way faulted; I feare it is rather in omiſsions through forgetfulneſſe, then in any ſort by ouerreaching thruogh flattery.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3120:34"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3120:34"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>HEB. 9.27.28.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>And as it is appointed vnto all men once to dye, and then comes the iudgement: So Christ was once offered to take away the ſinnes of many, and vnto them that looke for him, ſhall he appeare the ſecond time without ſinne vnto Saluation.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Context lyes thus. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle to ſhew the excellency of Chriſt the high Prieſt of the new Teſtament aboue the high Prieſt of the old Law, hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred a large compariſon betwixt them: the cheife things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are compared are three. Firſt, the Sanctuary, whereinto they entred. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the matter which they offered. Thirdly, the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of offerings. The Leuiticall high Prieſt entred into a Sanctuary made with handes; Chriſt into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb facs="tcp:3120:35"/> it ſelfe figured by that Sanctuary: the high Prieſt offered the bloud of beaſts; Chriſt his owne blood for a price of redemption: the Leuiticall high Prieſt offered often, becauſe his Sacrifices were imperfect; Chriſt but once, becauſe by that one oblation he hath perfected for euer them that be ſanctified: therefore is he a more excellent high Prieſt. Now this laſt point of his once offering is farther illuſtrated by a compariſon of likes in the text now read; the ſumme whereof is this; that as by Gods ordinance men dye but once; ſo by the ſame appointment of God was Chriſt but once offered.</p>
                  <p>The parts of the text, as of all other plenary com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſons are two, a <hi>Protaſis</hi> (.i.) the firſt part of the ſimilitude which is brought to illuſtrate: An <hi>Apodoſis</hi> (.i.) the ſecond part which is illuſtrated. In the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſis</hi> verſ. 27. there are theſe foure things obſerueable (for touching the <hi>Apodoſis</hi> ver. 28. time will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to ſpeake) firſt, the ground or Cauſe of Death; Gods appoyntment. Secondly, the ſubiect of death, Man; Thirdly, the Number of dyings, once. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Conſequent of death; after that comes the iudgement.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Doctrine.</note>It is appoynted. So hath Gods hand, and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance a ſpeciall ſtroke in our death: Our Sauiour <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.29. teſtifieth of <hi>Sparrowes,</hi> that not one of them falls to the ground by the hand of the fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, but by Gods prouidence and ſpeciall appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; how much leſſe a man more worth then many <hi>Sparrowes?</hi> And that place is knowne<note n="a" place="margin">Iob. 14.5.</note> 
                     <hi>Mans dayes are determined, and the number of his moneths is with God; he hath ſet him his boundes which he cannot
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3120:35"/> paſſe.</hi> More proofe needes not amongſt vs Chriſtians that haue learnt to acknowledge a ſpeciall proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, extending it ſelfe to euery action, and accident of mans life.</p>
                  <p>And here firſt are controlled two heatheniſh opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> of men bearing the face of Chriſtians. The firſt is of them, that impute this, and ſuch like euents to the diſpoſition of fortune the Idoll of the heathen. An heatheniſh and Bruitiſh conceit ouer burning all grounds of patience, faith, piety and religion. For Confutation, that one place touching that which we call chance medly in death abundantly ſufficeth,<note n="a" place="margin">Deut. 19.5.</note> If a man goe to the wood with his neighbour to hew wood, his hand ſtrikes with the Axe to cut downe the tree; the head flies from the helue, and ſmites his neighbour that he dieth: I<note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 21.13.</note> the Lord (ſaith God) haue offered that man into the hand of the ſlayer; what can be more caſuall in reſpect of the meanes, and yet hath Gods prouidence a ſtroke therein.</p>
                  <p>A ſecond error is of thoſe, that haue lift vp nature, and naturall cauſes in this kind, to ſhoulder out Gods prouidence from all working in the death of men. And theſe giue vnto God no more but a generall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence into ſecond cauſes; ſuppoſing them to worke according to that order ſet in them in the firſt Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And theſe men in death violent or naturall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge no ſpeciall worke of God ordering and diſpoſing ſecond cauſes to their euents: but impute all to diſtemper of body wherby diſeaſes are brought vpon vs, which of themſelues worke the diſſolution of the body. But ſee we what the Scripture teacheth, It is<note n="c" place="margin">Deut. 18.22.</note> 
                     <hi>The Lord that ſmites with conſumptions, and
<pb facs="tcp:3120:36"/> agues, and burning feuers:</hi> and<note n="a" place="margin">2. Sam. 12.15.</note> the Lord ſtroke <hi>Dauids</hi> child with ſickneſſe; that though it be true, our death is wrought by theſe as meanes, yet Gods hand hath the chiefe ſtroke in theſe immiſſions. And hereof it is, that we ſee many dye in their full ſtrength, their breaſtes full of Milke, and their bones full of Marrow, as <hi>Iob</hi> 21.23.24. without bodily di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes; ſome alſo viſited with deadly ſickneſſes, as<note n="b" place="margin">Iſay. 38 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> and yet recouered: the Lord would teach vs heereby, that ſickeneſſes and bodily diſeaſes are but his arbitrary inſtruments, which he vſeth or not vſeth at his owne pleaſure, to bring his purpoſe to paſſe. To Conclude, let this euer be holden as a principall by all Chriſtians, that howſoeuer our death is ordinarily brought vpon vs by ſickneſſe, decay of nature, or other inferiour meanes, yet are they all ſwayed and ordered not onely by a generall influence, but euen by a ſpeciall ordinance, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of God; theſe being but his inſtruments whereby he bringes his appointments to their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> Secondly, this doctrine muſt be vnto vs all an argument of patience and Contentment, whenſoeuer God ſhall by death depriue vs of friendes how neare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſoeuer ioyned vnto vs; as at this time God hath taken from ſome a bountifull Maſter, from ſome a kind friend, from the Country a Magiſtrate, from vs all a Chriſtian brother; our duty is with patience to ſubmit to this appointment, and good pleaſure of our God, conſidering that in their death the will and ordinance of God is accompliſhed. I know that in ſuch Caſes naturall affections will ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3120:36"/> Neither are they ſimply to be blamed, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſo good warrant from the will of God, inſtinct of Nature, practiſe of Chriſt, and his Saints. It is ſayd of our Sauiour<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 11.35.</note> that ſeeing the lamentation of the people ouer <hi>Lazarus,</hi> himſelfe had his ſhare in weeping. And of <hi>Abraham</hi> it is written<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 23.2.</note> that hee mourned for <hi>Sara</hi> her death: and of <hi>Ioſeph</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 50.</note> that he kept a ſeuen dayes ſolemne lamentation for his father <hi>Iacob.</hi> And it was a ſenſeleſſe errour of the <hi>Storckes</hi> grounded vpon their heatheniſh fate, that a wiſe man ſhould not ſuffer himſelfe to be mooued with any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, though neuer ſo lamentable. The Apoſtle was otherwiſe minded<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 1.30.</note> where he reckons this ſame Stoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call indolence amongſt the vices accompanying a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate mind. And ſurely if there be any of vs found ſo ſtockiſh, as whom loſſes of this nature moue not to mourning, I ſay not as <hi>Paul,</hi> he ſheweth himſelfe graceleſſe, but which is more, almoſt vnnaturall. And for this gentleman deceaſed, not to preſſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars vpon Children, I feare too much giuing the raines to ſorrow, when we ſhall conſider the care he hath euer ſhewed of the Countries good in affayres of Common-wealth; how ſpeedy in diſpatch of buſineſſes of the Kingdome, methinkes wee ſhould not chooſe but bewaile the loſſe of ſo prouident a guide, as members in the body are touched eſpecially with loſſe of their chiefeſt fellow members. Yet this withall let vs all remember; as well they that are neareſt touched, as thoſe that are farther of woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that Chriſtian ſorrow muſt in ſuch caſes haue a double aſpect; one caſt on our loſſe, the other lift vp to Gods appointment. When wee looke on our
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3120:37"/> loſſe, he ſhall bee an vnnaturall child, that cannot bewaile, the loſſe of ſo kind a father; an vnworthy member of the ſtate that laments not the fall of ſuch rulers in the Country; But yet if we ſhall looke vp to him whoſe hand hath ſwayed theſe things, and by whoſe appointment death hath ſeazed on him, me thinkes again we ſhould a little bridle affections, leſt they carry vs to impatience, and diſcontentment at this worke of God. It is ſaid of <hi>Dauid</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. that when God had ſtricken the child, which <hi>Vriahs</hi> wife bare him, with ſickeneſſe; he faſted and prayed, and wept and would not be comforted. For thus he apprehended that prediction of <hi>Nathan</hi> as implying the condition ordinary in ſuch threatenings; for who can tell (ſaith he) whether God will haue mercy on the child that he may liue. But when he ſaw the eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Gods will, and reſolute determination, he left off mourning, and went to praiſe God. Beloued, we now ſee Gods determinate appointment in this Gentleman; it ſhall be our duty patiently to ſubmit to his moſt holy, and iuſt diſpoſitions, and take we heed leſt looſing the bridle to naturall affections, they carry vs not beyond all bounds of right, reaſon and religion. What ſaith th' Apoſtle<note n="a" place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.13.</note> I would not haue you ignorant as concerning them that ſleepe, to ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row as men without hope: as if he had ſayd: Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate lamentations are fitter for Heathens, that know no life but this, then for Chriſtians that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a ioyfull reſurrection. It is noted of the Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 50.</note> that they mourned for <hi>Iacobs</hi> death 70 daies; of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> that he lamented him ſeuen dayes onely: ſome man perhaps will thinke <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſcarce naturally af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3120:37"/> that ſo ſoone ended his mourning, when the Egyptians, ſtrangers to him, ſo long drew on their lamentation. But behold the difference betwixt a hopeleſſe heathen, and a beleeuing Chriſtian: The Egyptians mourne vnmeaſureably, as thinking death to be a deſtruction of all things; <hi>Ioſeph</hi> as a Chriſtian, hopefully expecting the promiſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. And let vs that haue cauſe to expect a comfortable reſurrection of this Chriſtian Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, labour by conſidering Gods holy appointment to moderate our priuate griefes, and quietly to reſt in Gods holy determinations.</p>
                  <p>Yet let me a little farther preſſe this point of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: I ſay not onely that we ſhould moderate our griefes; but euen vpon this ground, becauſe God hath appoynted, practiſe patience. There is a kind of patience euen in people, that are heatheniſh; it is grounded commonly vpon the ineuitable neceſſity of ſuch like euents: Such a kind of patience or ſtupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity rather was that of <hi>Stoicks,</hi> death was neceſſary; life not reuocable; therfore vaine are all lamentations. And ſuch a like patience ſo grounded you ſhall ſee in our people. Well, there is no remedy; we are borne to dye; ſorrow will not helpe it: a good plauſible ground for patience in Reaſon. But know we, religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous patience hath another ground <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39. <hi>I was dumbe</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) and opened not my mouth: why? becauſe thou O Lord didſt it.</hi> This is Chriſtian pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to moderate our affections vpon this ground, becauſe we know it is the Lord that doth it; and death of friends betides vs by Gods appointment. <hi>It is appoynted to all men once to dye.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:3120:38"/>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> There are ſundry other vſes inferred by Gods ſpirit vpon this doctrine, that God hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted our death. <hi>Iob</hi> hauing at large treated of this point, thus inferres for his owne vſe: ſeeing God hath numbered my dayes, and determined the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of my moneths, decreed my death and diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Therefore all the dayes of mine appoynted time will I waite<note n="a" place="margin">Iob. 14.14.</note> vntill my change ſhall come: his meaning is, that his whole life ſhould be nothing but a Continuall meditation of death. Our people haue taken vp an euill by word; when they will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe their vtter and extreme forgetfulneſſe of a thing not thought of, they vſe this compariſon: I thought as little of it, as of my dying day. Alas, and is that dying day of all things leaſt thought of? Haue we not euery day ſpectacles of our Mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? and carrie we not in our boſomes the principles of our diſſolution? how comes it to paſſe then, that the day of death ſhould be of all things leaſt thought of, and fartheſt out of remembrance? and yet it is too true, as appeares by thoſe long hopes wee promiſe to our ſelues. Almoſt no man ſo old, or ſo diſeaſed but hee thinkes hee may draw on one yeare longer. A dangerous dreame as euer Sathan could ſend vpon men, taking away all care of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, and opening a gappe to all diſſoluteneſſe of life, and Conuerſation: take we heed of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>4</label> I might alſo hence inferre as our Sauiour doth <note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 9.4.</note> that while the day laſts wee ſhould worke the workes of God, becauſe there comes a night when as no man can worke. He alludes to the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tome
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3120:38"/> and vſe of men as <hi>Dauid</hi> hath expreſſed it in the <hi>Pſalme,</hi> the ſunne ariſeth, &amp;c. Man goeth out to his worke, and to his labour vntill the Euening; at night when darkeneſſe hath couered all things, he retires him to his reſt, becauſe he wants day light to direct him in working. So is the terme of euery mans n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>turall life; God hath giuen it to the ſons of Men, that therein they ſhould worke things plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vnto God. Whiles this day laſteth, worke we the workes of God. There comes a night vpon vs, that couers all with darkeneſſe, and leaues no time for men to worke in: Therefore ſayd the Apoſtle, while we haue time<note n="a" place="margin">Gal. 6.</note> let vs do good; and <hi>Salomon,</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Eccl. 9.10.</note> whatſoeuer thine hand ſhall find to do, do it with all thy power; for there is neither worke, nor inuention, nor know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, nor wiſdome in the graue whither thou goeſt.</p>
                  <p>Proceede we to the ſecond thing; the ſubiect of death; (Men (i.) all men. If any ſhall obiect that <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> were tranſlated that they ſhould not ſee death; and that Gods Children ſuruiuing at the day of iudgement ſhall not ſleepe, but ſhall be changed. 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. Let him conſider firſt, that <hi>Extraordinaria non euertunt regulam;</hi> a few extraordinary inſtances impeach not the courſe of generall ordinances. And howſoeuer the ſuruiuers at the laſt day ſhall not ſuffer death as it is a ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the ſoule and the body, yet as it puts an end to this animall life, they may be ſayd after a ſort to dye; at leaſt this change is vnto them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteed of death; or laſtly, the Apoſtle here ſpeakes of the ordinary courſe as it is now ſtabliſhed amongſt men by the appointment of God.</p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:3120:39"/>
                  <p>Now mankind in Scripture are all ranged into theſe two ranckes; Elect and Reprobate, Beleeuers and Vnbeleeuers; And of both ſorts it is true that the Apoſtle here ſpeakes; it is appoynted vnto them all once to dye.</p>
                  <p>Now becauſe it may ſeeme ſtrange, that Gods Children freed by Chriſt from the wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e curſe of the Law, ſhould yet be ſubiect to a neceſſity of dying, it ſhall not be amiſſe a little to enquire the reaſons of this Gods ordinance in reſpect of his Children.</p>
                  <p>Papiſts as appeares in all their tracts of <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory,</hi> vſually thus explaine it; that Gods Children muſt therefore dye, becauſe by Chriſt they are freed from none but eternall puniſhments due for their ſinnes. As for temporall iudgements, as ſickneſſes, Death &amp;c. They ſtill remaine vnto vs in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of puniſhments; by ſuffering whereof we muſt expiate our veniall ſinnes, as they terme them: And therfore it is their conſtant Doctrine, that Chriſt hath ſatisfied for none but ſinnes mortall; freed vs from no puniſhment but Euerlaſting; there is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of ſatisfaction left for vs, whereby Gods iuſtice and wrath muſt by vs be appeaſed.</p>
                  <p>Now the Apoſtle<note n="a" place="margin">Gal. 3.13.</note> hath taught vs that Chriſt hath redeemed vs from the Curſe of the Law (i.) from the whole Curſe due for our ſinnes. And who can read <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. but he muſt acknowledge bodily ſufferinges to be a part of our Curſe. <hi>Iſay</hi> teacheth Chap, 53. that the Chaſtiſement of our peace was laid vpon Chriſt; (i.) the Chaſtiſement whereby our peace, and reconcilement with God was perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3120:39"/> wrought. And the Apoſtle<note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 10.11.14.</note> affirmes that Chriſt by his one offering of himſelfe hath perfected foreuer them that be Sanctified.</p>
                  <p>Yea take wee but euen Popiſh conceſſions in this kinde: they grant that Chriſt hath deliuered vs perfectly from the guilt of our ſinnes. Now the guilt is nothing but a Conſequent of ſinne, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we ſtand in account as ſinners, and are liable to puniſhment for our offences. Now then; hath Chriſt perfectly freed vs from the guilt of our ſinnes? then ſtand we as innocent in the ſight of God, and are reputed of God for Chriſtes ſake, as if wee had neuer commited our ſinnes, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo are freed from ſubiection vnto puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: For ſhall wee ſay the Lord puniſheth a man guiltleſſe? farre be it from the iuſt God to puniſh the guiltleſſe as the guilty, the guilt is remoued, therefore all puniſhment.</p>
                  <p>But wee ſee theſe temporall paines and death it ſelfe remaines to Gods Children after iuſtification?<note place="margin">Obiect.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is true,<note place="margin">Sol.</note> the things remaine the ſame for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but their habit, vſe, condition is altered: They remaine not in the nature of puniſhments properly ſo called; for they tend not to ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Iuſtice; nor as parts of the Curſe; from which Chriſt hath freed vs; but temporall paines remaine as preuentions, as admonitions, as reſtrainements, as inſtructions, as nurturings, as reducements, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batements of Corruption. Death not as the wages of ſinne to Gods Children, nor as a part of the Curſe; but as the period of miſery, and a gate into heauenly happineſſe. But leauing them, let vs ſee
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3120:40"/> for what ends the Lord hath appointed death for his owne Children.</p>
                  <p>One is, the aboliſhing of the reliques of ſinne, that euen after regeneration ſticke in vs. By a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wiſedome God hath ordained, that during the dwelling of the ſoule in the body, there ſhall be alſo a dwelling of ſinne in our mortall body, partly to exerciſe vs by reſiſting the aſſaults thereof, partly to ſhew vs from how great a bondage Chriſt hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vs: But by death hee puts an end to ſinne in reſpect of all practice and inhabitation. Through enuy of the deuill ſinne entred into the world, and death by ſinne: Through the wiſedome of God death puts an end to ſinning. And this is one end of this appointment of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> A ſecond is, to put an end to the ſenſible miſeries of this life; for as there continues a remanent of the old <hi>Adam,</hi> euen after grace; ſo ſome portion of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions ſtill remaynes to Gods Children; not as Papiſts teach, for ſatisfaction; but partly to giue vs a taſte of thoſe miſeries, from which Chriſt hath freed vs, partly to tame and ſubdue Corruption, partly to conforme to the Image of Chriſt; Now death brings an end to all ſenſible euills. And for this cauſe alſo hath God prouided death as a remedy, leſt too long endurance of euills, ſhould ouercome our patience.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, that the ſoule might be admitted into the preſence of God; which made <hi>Paul</hi> deſire<note n="a" place="margin">Phil 1.23.</note> to be diſſolued; becauſe he knew his ſoule ſhould perſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be admitted into the preſence of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> Now ſeeing God for theſe good ends hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3120:40"/> the death of his Saints, methinkes it ſhould teach vs contentment at leaſt, if not reioycing in the death of all thoſe that dye in the Lord. And ſurely if any man haue knowne and felt the miſery of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection vnto his ſinnes; the ſtrong rebellion of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption againſt grace; I doubt not but hee is thus minded, that in that reſpect; he would change con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions with the meaneſt of Gods Saints that haue dyed in the Lord. And therefore well is it with the dead; they reſt from their labours; their workes follow them; and which is not the leaſt bleſſing, they are freed from the miſerable bondage to Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</p>
                  <p>Now as touching the wicked, the Reaſon of their dying is; becauſe death is to them a part of the Curſe due to their ſinnes: and there muſt be an end put to their pleaſures in ſinning, &amp; a bringing of their ſoules to thoſe vnſufferable torments God hath prouided for impenitent ſinners.</p>
                  <p>And therefore I wonder not,<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> if as the wiſe man ſpeaketh, the very remembrance of death bee bitter vnto them: it is their iudgement, their Curſe, the end of reioycing, the very ſuburbes and gate that leades into Hell.</p>
                  <p>See we now the laſt thing (.i.) the conſequent of death. After that comes the iudgement. I hope I ſhall not need to vſe many words amongſt vs Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to euidence this truth being ſo plentifully taught in Scripture, conſented vnto by the Heathen, teſtified by our conſcience, euidenced by particular iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                  <p>The Scriptures are plentifull in this point; how
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3120:41"/> often occurre theſe and the like ſayings! God ſhall bring euery worke vnto iudgement, with euery<note n="a" place="margin">Ecleſ. 12. vlt.</note> ſecret thing whether it be good or euill. We muſt all appeare before the<note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.10.</note> iudgement ſeate of Chriſt, that euery one may receiue the things he hath done in his body, whether they be good or euill.</p>
                  <p>The Heathen had their tribunall after death; and <hi>Aeacus, Minos</hi> and <hi>Rhadamanthus,</hi> preſidents of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings therein.</p>
                  <p>Yea aske but the Conſcience of the vileſt Athieſt, it will be a thouſand witneſſes of this truth; how often are they filled with vnſpeakeable horrours e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in death? wherefore? but becauſe they know there is a iudgement that followes it. See but particular iudgements, which are as <hi>praludia iudicij vniuerſalis:</hi> the ouerthrow of <hi>Sodom;</hi> the deluge of the old world; particular iudgements on particular perſons, what elſe doe they teſtifie but a iudgement to come? ſome ſinnes are here puniſhed that wee might know there is a prouidence, and a iudge that takes notice; not all here puniſhed that wee might expect a greater iudgement to come.</p>
                  <p>Yea that very Confuſion of things as they terme it, which ſome haue brought as an argument to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw both prouidence and iudgement; <hi>(viz)</hi> the preſent proſperity of the wicked, and the afflicted e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of Gods Children; it is argument ſufficient in <hi>Pauls</hi> diuinity to proue a iudgement to come,<note n="c" place="margin">2. Theſ. 1.4.5</note> The preſent perſecutions of Gods children are an euident Demonſtration of a iudgement, to come; and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Eccle. 3.16.17.</note> before him, in his ſuruiew of vanities, I ſaw, ſayth he, a place of iudgement, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oe there was
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3120:41"/> wickedneſſe, a place of Iuſtice, and behold iniqui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty: what inferres he? therefore no prouidence? ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no iudgement to come? Nay; but the contrary, I ſayd in my heart, ſurely God will iudge the iuſt and vniuſt; for a time there is for euery purpoſe and for euery worke.</p>
                  <p>See we a little what this iudgement importes. Iudgement implies three things. Firſt, Examination, and withall diſcouerie of euery mans workes, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be<note n="a" place="margin">Eccl. 12. vlt.</note> good or euill; then<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.5.</note> come your cloſe and ſecret adulteries, then your priuie and coloured bribery, then your hypocriſie, then your euery euill worke to be ſcanned and examined. The<note n="c" place="margin">Apoc. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0.12.</note> bookes are opened; firſt, of Gods<note n="d" place="margin">Mal. 3.16.</note> remembrance, wherein are regiſtred euery of our ſinnes, euen to an<note n="e" place="margin">Math. 12.36.</note> idle word; ſecondly, of our owne Conſcience, which ſerues to bring in records againſt vs of all our vngodly deedes which wee haue vngodlily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, After Examination followes ſentence giuing. Firſt, of Abſolution to Gods Children, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer here laden with reproaches and ſcandals, condemned for Hypocrites. The Lord ſhall then euidence by fruites of faith, that ſure their faith was vnfained. Secondly of Condemnation vpon the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, here blearing the eyes of men with I know not what pretenſes of their good hearts and good faith to God. The Lord ſhall then make their madneſſe and diſſembling knowne to all men by lacke of true Good workes to grace their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded faith with all. <hi>Math.</hi> 25.35.42.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, After ſentence follows Execution (.i.) A happie admiſſion of Gods Children into poſſeſſion
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3120:42"/> of the kingdome prepared by the father, purchaſed by Chriſt Ieſus. Secondly, A heauy and vncomforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſmiſſion of all impenitent and incorrigible ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners into that lake that burnes with fire and Brime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone before the throne of God for euer and euer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Vſe.</note>Now Brethren, I could wiſh in applying of this doctrine I had a meaſure of the Apoſtles ſpirit, that I might with it pierce into the Conſciences of vs all. S. <hi>Paul</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.11.</note> hauing breifly mentioned this doctrine of laſt iudgement, thus ſayth, that by this terror he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded men. And ſurely if this terror perſwade not to repentance, I know not what will. The ſame Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 24.26.</note> treating of Iuſtice and temperance and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come before <hi>Foelix</hi> an Heathen, made him tremble and quake euery ioynt of him for feare of that iudge, whom by bribery and whoredome he had offended.</p>
                  <p>But we are fallen into the times S. <hi>Peter</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">2 Pet. 3.</note> ſpeakes of, wherein the doctrine of iudgement is holden a fable, and nothing but a meere policy to keepe fooles in awe. The wicked Iewes vpon denuntiation of a particular iudgement<note n="d" place="margin">Iſay 22.13.</note> are brought in thus ſpeaking, Come, ſay they, let vs eate and drinke; for to morrow by the Prophets fabling, we muſt dye. Muſt you dye? Ah wretch! And what followes death? After death comes Iudgement: and if thou haue any grace in thee; the very mention of it will make thee tremble.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Salomon</hi>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">Eccl. 11.9.</note> hauing to deale with ſuch like deſperate ſcoffers, thus rebuketh their Godleſſe practiſe: Goe to young man, if you muſt needes haue your ſwinge, on, reioyce and let thy heart cheare thee in the dayes of thy youth, walke in the wayes of thy heart,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3120:42"/> and in the ſight of thine owne eyes; But know, God for all theſe things will bring thee to iudgement. It is not a permiſſion, but an ironicall ſharp and reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, vrged by a ſeuere denunciation of a iudgement to come.</p>
                  <p>As if I ſhould now ſay to an vniuſt bribing Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, if any ſuch amongſt vs, goe to, ſeeing thou haſt ſold thy ſelfe to work wickedneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> eate vp the fleſh of the people; flea of their skins, break their bones, chop them in pieces as meate for the pot, as <hi>Micah</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Mic. 3.3.</note> ſpeaks oppreſſe the fatherleſſe, and let not the cauſe of the widow come before you; ſay with ſhame enough<note n="b" place="margin">Hoſ. 4.18.</note> bring bribes, fill your houſes with extortion: But know, it is appoynted to all men once to dye, &amp; then comes the iudgement. At that day thou ſhalt find, that a little of <hi>Samuels</hi> good Conſcience;<note n="c" place="margin">1 Sam. 12.3.</note> whoſe oxe haue I taken, whoſe Aſſe haue I taken, whom haue I done wrong vnto; or of whom haue I taken a bribe to blinde mine eyes withall? will doe thee more ſteed, then all the treaſures of wickedneſſe, wherewith thou haſt filled thine houſe.</p>
                  <p>As if I ſhould ſay to the Cormorants of the Country, build you houſes in deſolate places, ioyne houſe to houſe, land to land, Country to Country, till the poore can haue no dwelling amongſt vs: But know, that for all theſe things God will bring thee to iudgement: And then thou wilt wiſh as <hi>Ieremie</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Ier. 9.2.</note> that thou hadſt had in the wilderneſſe a cottage of a way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faring man, rather then all theſe ſumptuous buildings and large poſſeſſions, while the ſtone ſhall cry out of the wall, and the beame out of the timber ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer it, woe<note n="e" place="margin">Hab. 2.11.12.</note> vnto him that buildeth a Towne with
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3120:43"/> blood, and erecteth a City with iniquity.</p>
                  <p>As if I ſhould ſay to our ſcraping mercileſſe Vſurers; ſhut vp your bowells of compaſſion, and cauſe the eyes of the needy to fayle by vaine expectation of your releife; grinde the faces of the poore; buy them for ſiluer, yea for old ſhooes; liue vpon the ſweate of others mens faces. But know that for all theſe things God will bring thee to iudgement; and then thou ſhalt find one penny giuen in compaſſion of thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers want, will afford more comfort, then all the huge maſſes of ſiluer and gold, that by vſury thou haſt heaped together.</p>
                  <p>As if I ſhould ſay to our drunken toſpots, powre in ſtrong drinke, drinke and be drunken, ſpend your patrimonies at the Ale; But know, that for all theſe things God will bring you to iudgement.</p>
                  <p>As if I ſhould ſay to a beaſtly Whoremoger; fill thine eyes with adultery, and thy bones with rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; take thy pleaſure in dalliance, and fill thee with luſt: But know; that, whoremongers and adulterers God will Iudge. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.4.</p>
                  <p>As if I ſhould ſay to our blaſphemous ſwearers; go to; ſeeing you haue taught your tongues to ſpeake blaſphemies, ſweare the Puritane out of his Coate, &amp; thy ſelfe out of Gods kingdome; but know; it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted to all men once to dye, and then comes the iudgement.</p>
                  <p>Beloued in Chriſt Ieſus, I know not how theſe things moue you; but if there be any care of our ſoules me thinkes they ſhould worke in vs a care to depart from euill; that we may be found worthy to ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt at his comming.<note place="margin">Act. 17 30.31.</note> And ſurely if S. <hi>Paul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3120:43"/> vpon this ground moue not to amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; I ſee not what can remaine for vs, but a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full expectation of iudgement, and violent fire to deuoure vs.</p>
                  <p>The Lord for his Chriſts ſake giue vs all grace on whom his name is called to depart from iniquity; that ſeeing he hath appointed a day, wherin he will iudge the world in righteouſneſſe by that man, euen Ieſus, whom he hath appointed, we may all be admoniſhed in euery place to repent, and eſcape thoſe vnſuffera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble torments, that he hath prouided for vnbeleeuers; in that lake of fire that burnes for euer before the Throne of God. To the ſame God, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, holy Ghoſt, three perſons, one true, inuiſible, immortal and only wiſe God be all honour and glory for euer and euer Amen</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
